<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cause &amp; cure of offences in a discourse on Matth. 18:7 / by R. Kingston ...</title>
            <author>Kingston, Richard, b. 1635?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47481</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13419613</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13419613</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99495</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47481)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 460:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cause &amp; cure of offences in a discourse on Matth. 18:7 / by R. Kingston ...</title>
                  <author>Kingston, Richard, b. 1635?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Daniel Brown ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 58 and 74 are tightly bound with some loss of text in filmed copy.  Pages 50-75 are photographed from Trinity College Library, Dublin copy and inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XVIII, 7 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99495:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CAUSE &amp; CURE OF Offences: IN A DISCOURSE On
<hi>MATTH.</hi> 18.7.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>R. Kingſton,</hi> M. A. Prebendary of <hi>So<hi rend="sup">•</hi>.</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His
Majeſty.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 10.32.</bibl> 
               <p>Give no offence to the Jew nor to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, nor to the Church
of God.</p>
            </q>
            <q> 
               <bibl>Rom. 16.17.</bibl> 
               <p>Mark them that cauſe divſions and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, contrary to the
Doctrine ye have learned, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Daniel Brown,</hi> at the
<hi>Black Swan</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> without <hi>Temple-bar.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99495:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99495:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful SAMUEL ASTRY
<abbr>
                  <hi>Eſq</hi>
               </abbr> His Majeſties Coroner, and Attorney in His
Majeſties Court of Kings-Bench, and one of His Majeſties Juſtices of the
Peace for the County of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HO I have ſo deep a Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe many &amp;
extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Favours which you have been pleas'd to confer upon me, that I
know it impoſſible to make any proportionable retaliation, and think it
would be alſo more than <pb facs="tcp:99495:3"/> a venial ſin, to offer ſuch a
violence to Gratitude, as not to acknowledge them with all Thankfulneſs; yet
I muſt aſſure you and all the World, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which prevail'd with
me for this Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were fetch'd from Topicks of a far different nature.
The Diſcourſe is of a Pious and Publick Concernment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no
other Patron could be more ſutable, than one of ſuch a Sober and
Well-temper'd Zeal, and that with ſuch a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent care of the Publick 
<pb facs="tcp:99495:3"/> Peace and common good adorn your Station, as all that know you
muſt bear witneſs to.</p>
            <p>The Cure of <hi>Offences,</hi> and an endeavour to recover the Age
from the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of Miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; prejudice, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
it in a harmonious peace, and united Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will not go under a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other
Patronage, than of ſo Loyal a Subject to his Majeſty, a hearty
well-wiſher to the Doctrine &amp; Diſcipline of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> and one that by Inclination, as well as <pb facs="tcp:99495:4"/>
Authority, is an enemy to all that of malitious wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs offend againſt
ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Neither do I fear here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to derive (from the moſt invidious
perſon) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny envy upon you, or the imputation of flattery up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſelf;
ſince it is a well-known Maxime, that Honour as a ſhadow flies the
purſuer, but follows him cloſe that flies from it: and among thankful men,
Deſert will ſooner be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcried where it obſcures it ſelf, and
publiſhed with greater applauſe the leſs it is affected.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:99495:4"/>Sir, If theſe few and unpoliſh'd Papers, that in
all Humility and Thankfulneſs, and as a laſting Teſtimony of my due
Reſpects I here of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to you, may be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Public, in
reducing Diſſenters to a Venerable Eſteem of our Church, and an
una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous embracing all its Holy Sanctions, I have accompliſh'd my end; and
hope to obtain your pardon for making uſe of your Name to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance this
honeſt Deſign: <pb facs="tcp:99495:5"/> in confidence whereof, I ſhall never ceaſe
to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the Bleſſings of Heaven for your ſelf, your Virtuous
Conſort, and all your hopeful Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue; and take leave to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the
Honour of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Humble, Obedient, and thankful Servant, RICH.
KINGSTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99495:5"/>
            <head>THE CAUSE and CURE OF Offences.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>St. <hi>MATTH.</hi> 18.7.</bibl> 
                  <p>Wo be to the man by whom the offence cometh.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Diſciples of the holy and bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, hearing
their Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Maſter diſcourſe of his Death and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note place="margin">Mark 9.31.</note> like <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>'s Captains, every man
looks for a Seigniory: ſomebody they think muſt be Lord-Deputy on Earth,
when Chriſt is gone to his Glory; 
<note place="margin">34</note>and therefore ambitiouſly enquire,
who ſhould be the perſon dignified with ſuperiority in that Kingdom of 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99495:6"/> the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> which they ſuppos'd would now be
erected upon earth. One thinks his Merit ſhall prefer him; another, his
Intimacy; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his Affinity; another, his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niority: but our Saviour, who
knew their Thoughts, and underſtood their unwarrantable Deſignes was after
worldly Gain, and ſecular Grandeur, drives them from that unhallowed
inqueſt with Words and Signs too. Firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">35</note>With a <hi>Word</hi> of
Admoniſhment, <hi>The greateſt among you muſt be as one that
ſerves:</hi> and unleſs they lowred thoſe aſpiring thoughts, and
abandoned their ambitions deſigns after Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they could not
<hi>enter into the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> they could not truly and indeed be
his Diſciples, or deſerve the very name of Chriſtians. As if he had
ſaid, Should your Gifts and Graces prefer you, ſhould you obtain what you
wiſh, and be the uppermoſt Garments in the myſtical Body of Chriſt; yet
may you not contemn or deſpiſe your Underlings. But on the contrary, the
greater dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity you acquire, the more ſervice will be expected; the larger
portion <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99495:6"/> of Favour is beſtowed, the higher Obligation lies
on you to be benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to others; for herein you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the grand
deſign of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal goodneſs, who is unwilling the meaneſt perſon on
earth ſhould be loſt, that might with our indulgent and charitable methods
be recovered to the knowledge and exerciſe of Godlineſs.</p>
            <p>The next warning is by a <hi>Sign.</hi> A little Child coming in
his way, our Saviour ſets him in the midſt of his haughty followers;
ſaying, Unleſs they became as little Children in their innocency and
unconcernedneſs, Heaven was no place for them. As if he had thus reproved
their ſinful affectation of Dominion: You that aſpire to the higheſt
place in my Kingdom, if you perſevere ſo diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically oppoſite to the
Laws of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, the loweſt Claſs will be too good for you. And
leſt ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Grandees ſhould ſcorn to take their Copy from a
Childs hand, he tells them in what eſteem theſe Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are with him;
<hi>Receive a little one,</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>and you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me:
offend a little one, and you <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99495:7"/> offend me.</hi> Beware then,
whoever you are that pretend to belong to Chriſt, that you make not the fall
of others, ſteps for your ſelves to riſe by: That being great men, or
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving advantage by Authority, or the luckineſs of befriended
Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that you wrong not, nor offend, the genuine Babes of
Chriſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a temporal Happineſs, incur an endleſs Wo:
<hi>For wo is to the man by whom the offence cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words are the denuntiation of <hi>a ſad Curſe</hi>
againſt thoſe that <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize</hi> or <hi>offend</hi> Chriſt's
little ones: Yet notwithſtanding our duty is ſo plainly explicated and
repreſented in Gloſs, and Caſe, by the ſeveral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries of St.
<hi>Paul</hi> upon this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of our bleſſed Saviour; the words
being miſunderſtood by the Ignorant, and miſapplied by the Litigious, I
hope it will not be thought waſte of time to explain them.</p>
            <p>The Greek Grammarians tell us the word
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> properly ſignifies the
<hi>Prop</hi> or little piece of wood in a <hi>Trap</hi> or <hi>Pitfal,</hi>
that ſupports the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and being touch'd lets it fall;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ariſtoph. Suidas</hi> Lexic. voc.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but I ſuppoſe
naturally hath a more <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99495:7"/> general Notion, and ſignifies any
thing that makes one halt, or limp, or that occaſions a man to
<hi>ſtumble</hi> or <hi>fall,</hi> from
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>halt,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as from
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſuch like; wherefore 'tis
rendred ſometimes a <hi>Stumbling-block,</hi> that which in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and St. <hi>Peter</hi>
expreſſes by another Greek word,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it denotes then any thing done by
us, whereby another is hindred in his courſe of piety, in his way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.
So that to <hi>ſcandalize</hi> or <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend,</hi> is to diſcourage,
grieve, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict them, to ſtagger, and make them doubtful in their
thoughts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and by our Advice, or Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to miſlead them from
vertuous courſes, and to encourage others in ſinful practice.</p>
            <p>What this <hi>Woe</hi> or <hi>Curſe</hi> was which our Saviour
denounc'd againſt offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, we may eaſily underſtand by taking our
meaſures from the ſixth Verſe: For our Saviour could not meet with a
Metaphor near home to expreſs the horror of his indignation and reſentment
by: It ſeems the <hi>four Capital puniſhments</hi> uſed by the Jews,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> too
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aint colours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineate 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99495:8"/> his frightful figure with, and therefore borrows a word from
the Syriac Tongue, whoſe cuſtom it was in notorious caſes to drown
Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; <hi>He that offends one of theſe little ones,</hi> (ſaith our
Saviour) <hi>it were good for him that a Milſtone was hanged about his neck,
and be drowned in the depth of the Sea,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when the repeating the ſame
thing in two Synonymous words, much aggravates the ſence. Thus
<hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> his <hi>Scholiaſt</hi> informs us, that the
<hi>Grecians</hi> when they inflicted this puniſhment, put a weight upon the
criminals Neck: And our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, to ſhew how much he is offended at the
offence given to his little ones, appoints the weight to be a Milſtone of the
largeſt ſize, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mola
jumentaria,</hi> ſuch a one as was uſually turned about by the help of
Aſſes, which might ſink him to the loweſt Abyſs of miſery.</p>
            <p>Now this being compared with the words of the Text, it acquaints
us, that the heavieſt Woe, the bittereſt Curſe, and the hotteſt place
in Hell, is appointed for <hi>the man by whom the offence cometh.</hi> For
though it muſt <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99495:8"/> needs be that offences come, yet Gods
wiſe permiſſion of them does not hinder his juſt vengeance upon them,
as not laying any neceſſity upon the will of man, and conſequently not
leſſening his Guilt or penalty.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Jerom</hi> hath told us,<note place="margin">In Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar.
Matth. 18.</note> that this doom pointed at <hi>Judas</hi> alone, by whoſe
ſuddain and traiterous Plot, as our Saviour forewarned, all ſhould be
offended. But what need we ſettle it upon one man, when the foregoing words
tell us, that the whole world is <hi>full of offenders,</hi> full of offences;
corporeal offences, which holy <hi>David</hi> was beſet with, Traps, and
Snares in his way; ſpiritual of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which the Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi>
ſpy'd, when <hi>men were made to ſtumble at Gods Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are of two ſorts; <hi>active,</hi> or
<hi>paſſive:</hi> active, of themſelves, or by accident. Of themſelves
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>when the work and intent
both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vicious.</hi> So by
accident, <hi>when a good work ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears evil, or fails in ſome needful
cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paſſive offences</hi> are <hi>taken</hi> or
<hi>given.</hi> Given, by the broad offences of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Taken, by our own
Malice: <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99495:9"/> One, the offence of the <hi>little ones;</hi> The
other, the offence of the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees.</hi> The one attended with a
<hi>vae,</hi> the other with a <hi>Sinite:</hi> Wo be to thoſe that
<hi>give</hi> the little ones an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; but if the Phariſee <hi>take</hi>
an offence where none is given, <hi>wo be to himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To lay open the terms in a word; the little one is a <hi>weak
Chriſtian;</hi> the <hi>offence,</hi> an obſtruction or impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the
way of his Salvation; the <hi>wo,</hi> an <hi>endleſs torment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to rive this great <hi>Block</hi> in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, we ſhall
find ſeveral pieces big enough to <hi>ſtumble</hi> at; big enough to kindle
an everlaſting fire, to bring an everlaſting <hi>wo</hi> upon us: whether
we conſider the deportment of our <hi>Tongues</hi> or our <hi>Lives,
offences</hi> are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by both.</p>
            <p>I will begin with a <hi>mad Engine,</hi> that lies in a wet place,
yet vomits fire. The <hi>venome</hi> of other creatures are in their Tail, but
the poyſon of man is in his <hi>Tongue:</hi> There are men that <hi>have
adders poyſon under their lips;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 52.4.</note>
whoſe ſole employment is in miſchievous words; giving a looſe to a
dangerous precipitancy, <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99495:9"/> where they ſhould uſe the curb
of a religious reſtraint. St. <hi>James</hi> out of our own mouths will
inform us, that the leaſt part of our ſelves gives the loudeſt report.
<hi>The Tongue is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Member, but boaſteth great things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 3.5.</note> If the Soul be puffed up with haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, it
is the <hi>Tongue</hi> that ſpeaketh <hi>proud things;</hi> and when the
thoughts are conſpiring into a Mutiny and cloſe Rebellion, at laſt they
burſt out, <hi>With our Tongues we will prevail; who is Lord over
us?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 30.12.</note> To what unholy and irreligious
purpoſes is that uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful faculty of Speech perverted, and that which was
deſign'd for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Mankind, become the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſturber thereof?
that we have great cauſe to conclude with St. <hi>James, If any man offend
not in word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 3.2.</note> he is fit to be accounted
in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe that can inoffenſively govern the whole body. The
faireſt Garden is ſpoil'd without an Hedge. Had our Grandmother
<hi>Eve</hi> but ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in her Tongue, ſhe had not loſt her Paradiſe,
nor bequeath'd the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Legacy of ſin and miſery to her Poſterity.
<hi>Job</hi> obtained a victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over the Devil with ſilence: he 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99495:10"/> that fill'd his body with Ulcers, could not bliſter his
Tongue, nor exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate that <hi>unruly member</hi> to charge his Creator
fooliſhly. 'Tis the great policy of Satan, to continue our Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſallage by
the ſame methods by which he firſt procured it, <hi>viz.</hi> a phrenetick
Garrulity: we all fell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Eve</hi> could not hold her peace;
becauſe ſhe would ſay that to her Husband, ſhe had not learn'd of her
God. When broad chinks and cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys are ſeen in the walls of our Houſe, we
begin to fear its downfal; and why do we not as well the fatal Prognoſticks
of uncloſed Mouths? How many Chriſtian-ſouls have been cruſh'd to
death, yea, ſunk down to Hell? How many a credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Ear hath ſucked
offence in? how many Houſes have fallen into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and jars, for want of
ſtopping up the gaping chinks and cranneys of a wide Mouth? But that I may be
a little more particular, our <hi>Tongues</hi> are apt to <hi>offend,</hi> as
in many others, ſo chiefly in theſe things; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the broaching of
<hi>errour,</hi> or the concealment of <hi>truth,</hi> or in the <hi>raſh
publication</hi> of it; by vile <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny,</hi> 
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99495:10"/> by
corrupt <hi>Counſel,</hi> by <hi>Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> or by
<hi>Filthineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee what a large Field I am got into, and how many ſtones
of <hi>offence</hi> lie about it: and though <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſays, <hi>He
that removeth ſtones ſhall be hurt therewith;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.9</note> yet I go on to prepare the way of the
<hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>little ones;</hi> beſeeching you all to remember
that you are not at a Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick-lecture, to have your Ears tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; but at the
Chair and Tribunal of Chriſt, to have your offences ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, to have your
lives bettered. And now as I have been always care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful not to give
<hi>offence</hi> by making a <hi>Satyr</hi> on any religious Party, the ſame
method I ſhall ſtill purſue, as far as it conſiſts with my
<hi>duty</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, the peace and quiet of his <hi>Church,</hi> and the
diſcharge of my own <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the rank of <hi>offenſive Tongues,</hi> I will firſt
preſent you with the falſe Prophet, the teacher of Lies, which cauſeth
many unſtable Souls <hi>to erre from the faith once delivered to the
Saints;</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> (ſaith <hi>Malachi</hi>) <hi>are departed
out of the way,</hi> and then no wonder that the People <hi>ſtumble</hi> 
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99495:11"/> at Gods Law: ſome fat gobbet thoſe ſpiritual Guides
ſtep aſide for, and care not whom they miſlead for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. When
<hi>Phyſicians</hi> deſign to purge a Sucking-child, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the
Nurſe, and not the Child to take the Potion, that with more ſafety in the
Nurſes Milk the Child may receive the benefit of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine. The Devil is
no leſs skil'd in poiſoning the Babes of Chriſt; for thus the two great
Clerks of <hi>Rome,</hi> the voluminous <hi>Cardinals,</hi> and their
ſucceeding <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed corrupt Articles into our
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Creed,</hi> have taught people to ſhake off obedience to their
lawful Soveraign, and to expect Wreaths of Martyrdom for bloudy
Aſſaſſinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. 'Tis true indeed, they call us <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and
charge us with <hi>Schiſm</hi> in departing from their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but
theſe calumnies will eaſily be blown off, and like bullets ſhot againſt
Heaven, fall upon their own heads: for we withdrew not from them, till <hi>they
gave the offence</hi> by departing from the <hi>Catholick Faith.</hi> And to
prove this, I need no other teſtimony than their <hi>Tridentine</hi> 
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99495:11"/> Creed, which in thoſe Articles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they differ from
the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is neither <hi>true, ancient,</hi> nor
<hi>Catholick,</hi> but an entire Apoſtacy from it, and without
controverſie, <hi>is the moſt Catholick, and greateſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in the
Chriſtian-world.</hi> View it firſt in their Doctrine of
<hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation;</hi> an Opinion that upon due examination and
choice, no man can embrace without reproaching his Maker and Redeemer, by
renouncing his very Reaſon and outward Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: For to make me believe that
to be <hi>Fleſh</hi> which I ſee and taſte is <hi>Bread,</hi> is to turn
fool or madman; and for an <hi>unwarrantable</hi> Faith, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit both my
Reaſon and Senſe: and by the ſame reaſon they would ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie this
fond and abſurd Notion, a man may as well believe the <hi>Picture</hi> of a
man to be the man himſelf. If the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would lay aſide
their <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot,</hi> (the ſtrongeſt argument that ever
yet they brought to prove it) and tell us which of Chriſts Bodies it is that
is <hi>corporeally</hi> in the Sacrament, whether his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifi'd, or not
glorifi'd body, and clear it from all thoſe <hi>monſtrous
abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> 
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99495:12"/> which that opinion is guilty of, they
would greatly oblige us; for till they have done this, they muſt give us
leave to believe it a <hi>real</hi> and ſubſtantial
<hi>contradiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding Gods ſolemn prohibition againſt the
<hi>worſhip of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages</hi> delivered in fire, with Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Lightening,
on the Mount;<note place="margin">Deu. 27.15</note> yet in a direct oppoſition,
the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> command under <hi>dreadful Anathema's,</hi> that
religious worſhip be given to them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo. Azor.</hi> tom.
1. lib. 9. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſays, that the <hi>ſame</hi>
Worſhip is to be given to the <hi>Image</hi> of Chriſt, as to <hi>Chriſt
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sum. par. 3. q. 25. art. 3.</note> And this
is avouch'd by <hi>Pedro de Cabrera ſuper loc.</hi> to be the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of
their whole Church, and the contrary to be heretical.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zac. Bovir</hi> par. 2. reg. 1. p. 189.</note> Thus impudently
ſacrilegious dare they be, though the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Curſed be all
they that worſhip graven Images, and boaſt themſelves of Idols.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 27.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Again, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the uſe of the
ſacred Oracles to Laicks,<note place="margin">Concil. <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi> 22.
Seſſ. c. 8. 9 Canon. Ind. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pur. regul. 5.</note> and hath therefore
placed the <hi>holy Bible</hi> in the front of <hi>prohibited</hi> Books, and
<hi>Anathematiz'd</hi> all thoſe that ſhould dare to tranſlate it into
any Language vulgarly intelligible: <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99495:12"/> and to ſtrengthen
this <hi>ungodly</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, the Sons of that Church have ſuperadded many
<hi>ſlight</hi> and <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing</hi> expreſſions, tending to
leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the eſteem of <hi>God's holy Word.</hi> One tells us, that if the
Scriptures were not ſtrengthned by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Church,</hi>
they were of no more value than <hi>Aeſops Fables.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit.</hi> exam. de S. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, p. 47.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
of their Authors (inriched with the ſame brazen modeſty) ſays, <hi>that
the people were permitted to read God's Word, was the invention of the
Devil!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Periſ.</hi> de tradit. par. aſſert.
3.</note> Bluſh O Heavens, and be aſtoniſhed O Earth, at ſuch daring
impieties! Tell it not in <hi>Gath,</hi> nor in the Streets of
<hi>Askelon,</hi> leſt whole Chriſtianity be ſtigmatiz'd for a
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, through the wickedneſs of thoſe that bear the world in hand
they are the onely Catholick Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of depoſing Kings, diſpoſing their Kingdoms,
and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizing Subjects to deſtroy their lawful Soveraign, they not onely
ſtoutly deny even to death, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe us of ſcandalizing both them and
their Religion, in charging the act of one man as a blemiſh on the 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99495:13"/> whole Church. And for the more credit to their charge,
they vapour with a Decree of the <hi>Council of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> which (as
they ſay) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the murder of Crown'd Heads.<note place="margin">Concil.
Conſt. Seſſ. 15.</note> 'Tis true, by this Council the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Kings
is covertly forbidden, but tacitely implied; for it onely makes the horrid act
unlawful, where it wants the Judges Sentence: But if his <hi>Holineſs,</hi>
or any <hi>General of an Order,</hi> ſentence them, it renders the
proditorious act not onely Lawful, but Meritorious. And that this was but the
opinion of one man, <hi>viz. Mariana,</hi> is a grand miſtake; for 'tis a
Doctrine taught in their Schools, juſtified by their Practices, and
main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in their Writings, as might be made appear from <hi>Ribadenira,
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus, Windects, Stapleton,</hi> and the reſt of that lawleſs herd of
<hi>Ignatian Caſuiſts:</hi> Nay, 'tis a Doctrine whoſe bloudy hand can
never be concealed, nor the ſtain waſh'd off from their Church, whilſt
the triumphant Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fifth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues extant in
the world, which he made to his Cardinals in the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory</hi> upon
the barbarous Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99495:13"/> of <hi>Henry</hi> the
Third of <hi>France,</hi> after he was ſtab'd to death by <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> a
Dominican Fryer, aſſimilating it with the myſtery of the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and
Reſurrection, and with the acts of <hi>Judeth</hi> and <hi>Eleazar.</hi>
Again,</p>
            <p>When <hi>Gerrard</hi> deſign'd the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Prince of
Orange,</hi> he had encouragement, and bleſſing, from the <hi>Warden</hi>
of the Fryers at <hi>Tourny;</hi> and the Jeſuit his Apologiſt, ſays,
That <hi>Gerrard</hi> did that deed, <hi>pour la bien de vertu!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Campian</hi> the Jeſuit, having Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from <hi>Rome,</hi>
and aſſociated by <hi>William Parry,</hi> conſpired the death of Queen
<hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gordon, Chreiton,</hi> and <hi>Abercany,</hi> Jeſuits,
plotted the death of <hi>King James;</hi> and this traiterous deſign was
forwarded by two Breves from <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth: and Cardinal
<hi>Bellarmin</hi> calls <hi>Garnet,</hi> and his fellow <hi>Oldcorn,</hi>
Martyrs, and for ſuch are Regiſter'd in the Jeſuits Catalogue of Martyrs,
Printed at <hi>Rome,</hi> 1607. Of theſe ſanguinary Attempts, I could give
you inſtances <hi>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad nauſeam;</hi> but for the preſent let
theſe ſuffice.</p>
            <p>What hath been ſaid, I hope is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99495:14"/> to prove, that their bloudy Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of <hi>King-killing,</hi> is not
the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of one man only, but that ſome of all Orders in that Church have
bin guilty of it; and tho Charity may encline me to believe, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Loyal
perſons of the Romiſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, do abhor thoſe Jeſuitical
principles and practices, yet the Pope, nay, the whole Church cannot be
acquitted, till they have puniſhed thoſe Church-men of his, who have
publickly abetted ſuch treaſonable Conſpiracies, cenſured
<hi>Mariana</hi>'s, and ſuch other Books as have commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Regicides, to the
great ſcandal of Religion; and by his Pontifical decree, provided better for
the ſafety of Kings, than his Colledge of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have: for till
this be done, and they have given us as many years experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of their
Loyalty, as they have of their Treachery, 'twill be of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence
to believe them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent: For what faith, or truſt, can be repoſed in
thoſe men, whoſe Church perſwades them to be wicked, and covers all their
hell-bred Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances under the umbrello of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which does nothing
elſe but <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99495:14"/> give ſcandal to it, and bring upon
themſelves an endleſs Woe?</p>
            <p>Now having done with theſe kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Nurſes, I could gladly
break off this unſavoury Theme, but that there is <hi>another Sect</hi>
amongſt us, whoſe Poyſonous Doctrines are as baneful if we take not heed:
'Tis one of the preſent Troubles we groan under; a proud company of
male-contented Bablers (who are Prieſts of their own making, and the
ſictitious Idols of abuſed Phancies), having imbibed Seditious principles,
from them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Zealots have ſuck't not <hi>the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere milk of the
Word,</hi> I will be bold to ſay, but a poyſoned doſe of Schiſm and
Prejudice. Thus the Stars fall from Heaven, the waters below are turn'd into
wormwood, and the drinkers dye. What miſchievous offences have overſpread
the boſom of great Britain? What ſplenative rage, and opprobrious words,
are caſt on the face of Authority? What ſtumbling-blocks are daily thrown
out, to check harmonious Peace, and united Devotion, ſince troubleſome,
rebellious, and teſty Spirits were both <hi>indulged</hi> and applauded!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99495:15"/>'Tis now grown a neceſſary point of
Purity, to muzzle Aſſemblies into Schiſm and Faction, to ſnivel out a
<hi>demure Lye,</hi> inſtead of a holy Doctrine, to vent a <hi>Libel</hi>
inſtead of a Uſe, to bring in ſuſpition that <hi>Thames</hi> and
<hi>Tyber</hi> have joyn'd Channels, and that our Government, Rites, and
Liturgy, are wholly Romiſh, or Antichriſtian. With this <hi>ſoure
milk</hi> the Babes of Chriſt are publickly fed, and yet the
<hi>Non-conforming Presbyters</hi> would be thought no Offenders.</p>
            <p>The boyſterous Thunders of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſtrike not the top of
<hi>Olympus;</hi> but ſaucy Seducers are now found, that fear not to blaſt
the height of Majeſty, overthrow the Seats of Superiority, and tear
Allegeance out of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts; and inſtead of caſting St.
<hi>Peters</hi> Net into the wild luſts of <hi>Mars,</hi> tranſlate the
bleſſed <hi>Goſpel of Peace</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the iron language <hi>of Blood and
War, Trouble</hi> and <hi>Diſcord.</hi> Truly how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſuch <hi>clamorous
Zealots</hi> boaſt of the certainty of their <hi>Election,</hi> Chriſt hath
mark'd them with a <hi>woe</hi> of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. <hi>Woe to thoſe barbarous
Pilats that mingle blood with their Sacrifices; Woe to thoſe furious
Sampſons that muſt <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99495:15"/> have multitudes to periſh with
them;</hi> Woe to the <hi>Seducing Prophet,</hi> by whom the offence comes.</p>
            <p>But <hi>truth</hi> as well as errour may occaſion an offence;
good Counſel, like the Peach-tree, may bring forth poyſonous fruit in one
place, and wholſome in another. The meſſages of Heaven are oft compared
to ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of rain, which falling in due ſeaſon makes a plentiful year;
but ſcarcity follows unſeaſonable ſhowers: That which in one place
avails, in another annoys; it inricheth our fields, but dirtieth our ſtreets.
<hi>Woe be to thoſe Clouds</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>that ſend
ſuch ſhowers, as make foul work among us,</hi> but bring forth no
Fruit.</p>
            <p>A word ſpoken in due ſeaſon, and ſit place, hath an
excellent ſavour; but when both theſe are wanting, the audience goes away
worſe. Among others, there are three waies of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offences, even in the
publication of Truth. 
<list>
                  <item>1. Either by ſcrupulous Doctrine,</item>
                  <item>2. By bitter Rebukes, or</item>
                  <item>3. By perſonal Invectives.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, We have ſome that while they would be thought
<hi>Solid,</hi> do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99495:16"/> prove but <hi>ſaucy</hi>
Divines; on all occaſions they are ruſhing into the hidden Secrets of God,
and perplex their weak people with the thorny myſteries of <hi>Election</hi>
and <hi>reprobation;</hi> a doctrine which is fitly ranked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe
things that profit being unknown: Not that I deny, but there may be excellent
matter drawn from ſuch high Points; but the Brain muſt uſe her knowledge,
as ſhe doth her ſpittle, and vent no more of it, than may ſtand with the
bodies welfare. The bright countenance of <hi>Moſes</hi> was vayled, when he
was to deal with the people, whoſe benefit he prefer'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his own
applauſe. It were far better men obſcured the light of their knowledge and
learning, than that they ſhould diſplay it to <hi>affright</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or
<hi>dote about queſtions that breed envy and evil ſurmiſes.</hi> There
are in our Religion ſeveral Myſteries, and holy Scripture contains many
things above the reach of our quickeſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities; and in nothing more men
give offences, than in going about to <hi>explain Myſteries,</hi> and give an
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſuch things, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves acknowledge to be
<hi>incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible.</hi> 
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99495:16"/> And this is not my opinion
only, but (what ſome men will think ſtrange) 'tis Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s
alſo: for at the cloſe of his Doctrine of decrees, he adviſes Miniſters
to be very wary of propoſing this Doctrine to the people, for fear of
<hi>giving them offence and diſturbance:</hi> For if a man (ſaith he)
ſhould come into a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and thus beſpeak them: <hi>Friends and
Chriſtians, I am here ſent to you to</hi> preach the Goſpel; <hi>but I
muſt acquaint you aforehand, that there are but two or three among you,
thoſe</hi> (that are the Elect) <hi>that are like to be ever the better for
my Miniſtry; and as to the reſt of you, there's</hi> Horribile Decretum,
<hi>a dreadful Bar in your way,</hi> that all the Preaching in the world can do
you no good; <hi>and the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt,</hi> apply to them as you
will, <hi>can never prove available to your Salvation:</hi> His hearers would
run out of the Church, and cry <hi>the man were out of his Wits.</hi> This
juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment was extorted from the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va-Oracle,</hi> by an
ingenious reflection on his own Scheme, and the unhappy conſequence he
<hi>foreſaw</hi> it would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce; and I heartily wiſh his caveat 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99495:17"/> might be obſerved by his followers. For certainly it
would conduce more to the Glory of God, and the Intereſt of Chriſtianity,
if men would let thoſe things that are myſterious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſo, and employ
themſelves in promoting Juſtice, Honeſty, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Devotion; and
inſtead of <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating</hi> one another into the <hi>Regions of
darkneſs,</hi> to do offices of love and friendſhip one towards another,
and <hi>adorn</hi> the Doctrine of our Saviour by our mutual good-will, and
ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs to our brethren.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Publick Rebukes, (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs like <hi>Jonathans</hi> Rod
they be dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in honey) offend all. The rough hands of <hi>Eſau</hi> were
unfit for Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority. Sinners like blind men muſt be led gently, not haled
by violence. What gets the Merchant by a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt? Who had not rather drink
at a ſweet Fountain, than a briniſh Sea? who raiſes a fallen man, that
bows not himſelf down? ſleepers ought to be waked gently: for as frightful
and violent rouſings have driven many into wild Lunacies; ſo wounded and
broken hearts are caſt into deſpair, prophane ones into fury and
viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99495:17"/> by <hi>the offenſive harſhneſs of a
bitter reprover.</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That <hi>too unreaſonable, or
importunate reproof, is apt to make the Sinner firſt ſhameleſs, and then
obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Liſt of the Beatitudes, we are to be firſt Meek, and
then Merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: we muſt be <hi>merciful</hi> to the Soul of our brother; but
we muſt have the <hi>Spirit of meekneſs</hi> in our ſelves firſt. To
correct other mens offences in <hi>anger,</hi> is to be guilty of greater than
theirs. How have thoſe grim Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors forgot this, that vomit nothing but
<hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimſtone!</hi> that breath nothing but
<hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</hi> that thus unadviſedly skare
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed ſouls from the door of <hi>Chriſts mercy!</hi> The Jews
have a ſaying, It were better we were cold in our graves, than we ſhould
make our brother pale in a publick aſſembly: Our reproofs are allowed to
glow with the ardent deſires of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours <hi>reformation;</hi> but if
we ſuffer them to grow ſo hot as to bliſter the skin of his
<hi>Reputation,</hi> it is <hi>reproaching,</hi> not <hi>reproving.</hi> God
Almighty, I am <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99495:18"/> ſure, hath a quarrel to thoſe rigorous
maſters, <hi>that have not ſtrengthened the diſeaſed, not healed the
ſick, nor bound up that which was broken;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze.
34.4.</note> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a <hi>pious condeſcention</hi> to their
Infirmities, have by bitter taunts <hi>encouraged</hi> them to preſume, or
<hi>frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> them to <hi>deſperation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Perſonal invectives offend all: our bleſſed Lord
brought not his Traitor upon the ſtage in publick view, but deciphers him in
general terms, <hi>One of you ſhall betray me.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> would
have his <hi>Timothy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke and intreat all;</hi> but gives him no
commiſſion by a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection to <hi>ſcandalize</hi> any. We are
Fiſhermen, and muſt caſt in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bait, without deſign to wound any
ſingle perſon in the common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem; leſt inſtead of <hi>reforming
his vices,</hi> we give him a <hi>real offence,</hi> and make the ſore rankle
worſe for being vanned with the publick Air. How ill-becoming is it then in
our low-ſpirited <hi>predicants,</hi> that chooſe a Text on purpoſe to
begin a braul! and <hi>Raiſe</hi> a Doctrine to revenge ſome
<hi>Peccadillo</hi> on their ſilent Auditors! This is <hi>to Preach our
ſelves, and not <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99495:18"/> Chriſt, and him crucified;</hi> to
bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to contempt Gods ſacred Ordinance, and to make the more ſerious
part of our diſcourſes to be ſlighted, for blending our little
<hi>quarrels</hi> with the <hi>holy meſſage,</hi> and driving on ſome
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of our own, under the mask of a more holy Employment. One would think
the fooliſhneſs of this Vice might obſtruct a further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs: For it
neither procures us Friends, nor removes our Feuds; but on the contrary,
enrages our enemies, and makes them aſſume an unjuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, rather
than fall under a juſt ſhame. In whatſoever Sphere we move, 'tis good
neither to bite nor fawn, but rather ſubſcribe to him that ſaid, 
<q>Nolo minor me timeat, deſpiciatur major.</q> An even and
humble carriage to all men, eſpecially whilſt diſpenſing the ſacred
Word, makes men look like <hi>Embaſſadors of Chriſt,</hi> and ſuch
whoſe Religion is not vain, ſpending it ſelf in idle &amp; frivolous
taunts, but is circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed within the bounds of Charity, that will neither
hear nor ſpeak any thing that may directly occaſion an
<hi>Offence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99495:19"/>Our bleſſed Saviour reſtraining the
<hi>hoſtility</hi> and <hi>murther</hi> of the <hi>Tongue,</hi> threatens
<hi>hell-fire</hi> to them that call their brother <hi>fool.</hi> Meaning, that
all language which does really, and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, diſgrace him in the
greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, is as directly againſt the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Goſpel, as
killing a man was againſt the Juſtice and Severity of the Law: And although
the Word it ſelf way be uſed to reprove the indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and careleſs
follies of an idle perſon; yet it muſt be uſed onely <hi>in order to his
amendment,</hi> by an <hi>authorized</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and within the limits of a
juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, upon juſt occaſion, and ſo as may not do him miſchief
in the event of things. And though ſome men juſtifie their perſonal
rebukes, from examples in Scripture, as from our Saviour calling his
Diſciples <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, and St.
<hi>James</hi> uſing <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>vain
man,</hi> the ſame in ſignification with the forbidden Raca; and St.
<hi>Paul</hi> call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Galatians mad, fooliſh</hi> and
<hi>bewitched;</hi> and Chriſt calling <hi>Herod Fox,</hi> &amp;c. Yet is
their practice not warranted hereby, unleſs it be done in the <hi>ſome
manner,</hi> and with the <hi>ſame mind:</hi> if it be for correction and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99495:19"/> toward perſons deſerving it, and by perſons
whoſe <hi>authority</hi> can war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant it, and this be done prudently,
ſafely, and uſefully, it is not contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but when men upon all
occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons revile an offending perſon, leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſowring his
ſpirit and his life, deſpiſing his infirmities, tragically expreſſing
his lighteſt Miſdemeanour, being tyrannically declamatory and intolerably
angry for a trifle: Theſe are ſuch who, as <hi>Apollonius</hi> the
Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher ſaid, will not ſuffer the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding perſon to know when
his fault is <hi>great,</hi> and when 'tis <hi>little:</hi> For they who always
put on a Supreme anger, or expreſs the leaſt anger with the higheſt
reproaches, make no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between him that robs a Houſe, and him that
breaks a Glaſs. <hi>Non plus oequo, non diutius oequo,</hi> was a good rule
for reprehenſion of ſinners. He that reproves too <hi>long,</hi> does
reproach and <hi>harden</hi> the Offendor; he that does it too
<hi>bitterly,</hi> betraies his own <hi>anger,</hi> and is guilty of
<hi>rayling;</hi> if too <hi>loud,</hi> he is <hi>immodeſt;</hi> if too
<hi>publick,</hi> he is <hi>unmanly;</hi> and if too <hi>perſonal,</hi> he is
<hi>imprudent,</hi> for no clamorous perſon can be wiſe. The cure of which
evil <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99495:20"/> conſiſts in following St. <hi>Pauls</hi>
Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Let all bitterneſs and clamour be put away.</hi> Spare the
<hi>perſon,</hi> but not the <hi>ſin;</hi> for he carries a witneſs in
his boſom, that tells him he is the <hi>man</hi> againſt which the arrow of
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof is ſhot; whereas the oppoſite dealing will rather <hi>ſhame</hi>
the ſinner, than <hi>amend</hi> him. <hi>Voe increpanti,</hi> Woe to the
bitter reprover by whom the offence comes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Yea, and <hi>non increpant</hi> too; our very ſilence
may give an offence: But one Erring man is wink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at, ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi>
and the whole Church is wounded. What mercy is this, to diſpence with one,
and to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroy all! How oſt is all <hi>Iſrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> puniſht for the fault of one
<hi>Acha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Concealed enormities
imply a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion that encourageth to perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and now that which
might have been blown away with a word is grown a rooted example. Suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prophets had Jury in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi>
time <hi>that ſmooth'd up the people in lyes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Prophets that ſhould have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heads,</hi> and indeed were nothing bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tayls;</hi> nothing but tails to
cover fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs:<note place="margin">Iſai. 9.15.</note> Or as
<hi>Ezekiel</hi> amplifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 13.4.</note> 
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:99495:20"/> that homely Caracter, They
were grown <hi>Foxes with great tails,</hi> as ſit as could be to hide or
wipe away the noyſomneſs of a ſinning people, as Foxes with their
dangling ſingles do their filth, that they may not be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their loud
threatning enemies. O Mercenary wretch, ſaith St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> thou
ſaweſt a Wolf endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Flock of Chriſt, and ranneſt away! How
ran I away? will ſome old <hi>Levite</hi> reply, that ſticks faithfully to
his Glebe and vails; why, here I live, here am I Canonically reſident; how do
I run away? That Father will tell you, you are then fled, when your lips are
<hi>ſinfully cloſed;</hi> when either to keep a <hi>commodious friend,</hi>
or to ſhun a <hi>furious enemy,</hi> ſome leud man ſhall be let alone in
his impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. How many <hi>luxurious wantons</hi> might have been chaſt and
<hi>regular?</hi> How many in whom the ſparkling Canary hath drowned
<hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> might have ſtart up rigid Paterns of
<hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Sobriety!</hi> How many gripple
<hi>Mammoniſts</hi> might have become renown'd Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles of Bounty, if ſome
holy and wholſome tongue had given a timely <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99495:21"/> aſſault,
and come in to the reſcue of the precious Image of God, ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
defac'd by an unchriſtian conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance? But on the contrary, that which is our
ſhame, and ſhould be our ſorrow, we ſuffer Gods Name to be
diſhonoured and blaſphemed, Chriſts body to be torn and mangled afreſh
with Oaths, and his truth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired with impious Abſurdities, yet never open
our mouths in their vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication! What prepoſterous madneſs is this!
ſhould our friends Coat but ſit diſorderly on his back, we would
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently rectifie the immodiſh errour: But his life is wretchedly
<hi>debauch'd</hi> and <hi>diſſolute,</hi> and we never ſtop him in this
dangerous Carreer. Is not the Soul of more worth than the Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? this at
moſt but an unfaſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able blemiſh, but the other fearful and extreamly
perilous. Might not the Jew ſuffer <hi>the beaſt of his Neighbour to fall
and periſh;</hi> and ſhall we ſuffer the Soul of our brother to be undone
to all eternity? <hi>God forbid;</hi> let us rather by good advice, ſnatch
them as <hi>brands out of the fire.</hi> And this is a duty not confin'd to
thoſe of the Miniſterial Function onely, who muſt <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99495:21"/>
needs want the frequent and requiſite opportunities, but indiſpenſibly
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon all men who <hi>fear God,</hi> and wiſh the good of humane
Souls.</p>
            <p>Eaſie obſervation will make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that the neglect of
this Duty hath cauſed the greateſt <hi>degeneracy</hi> in Chriſtianity,
and made Religion eſteemed the moſt inconſiderable part and end of our
lives: That ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral remiſneſs viſibly in Piety, is chiefly, if not
wholly, to be attributed to this ſort of ſlaviſh Compliance, which even
Conſcientious men are too apt to admit of, in relation to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens vices;
by which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a currant ſtamp and approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whileſt a prudent
reproof would certainly work a Shame, if not a Conviction in the ſinner. Now
this unfriendly and unchriſtian Cuſtom, is uſually warranted upon the
<hi>preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Civility</hi> of the Age, and <hi>Freedom of
converſation,</hi> which allows every man an uncontroulable priviledge of
<hi>living his own life:</hi> And then it muſt be no leſs than
<hi>rudeneſs</hi> and <hi>imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence,</hi> to introduce any religious
Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Indifferency here makes the <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99495:22"/> beſt company; and
any reluctant diſlike of Sin, ſpoils and diſturbs it: And ſo
<hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf muſt now be excluded, as an unfit Companion for
<hi>Publicans and Sinners.</hi> All concern for his Honour muſt out of
<hi>civility</hi> be diſclaimed, even by his own fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, becauſe <hi>to
the Jew he is a ſtumbling blook, and to the Greek Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher
fooliſhneſs.</hi> As the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Graces and Gifts of Gods holy
Spirit are almoſt levelled with moral Virtues, ſo thoſe
<hi>Goſpel-duties,</hi> ſuch as the fear of death could never yet
diſpence with, muſt now be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and limited, by the rules of a
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendedly civil, <hi>i. e.</hi> a licentious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. Nay, ſo far
has this endea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring and obliging humor prevail'd, that men are afraid to
ſtand up in the Cauſe of God, leſt they ſhould affront his
<hi>Enemies;</hi> but muſt live in conſtant <hi>rebellion</hi> to their own
<hi>Conſciences,</hi> on the petty obligation of <hi>Civility</hi> and
Manners falſly ſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Whereas according to the rule of <hi>good
Manners,</hi> that is certainly th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
higheſt rudeneſs, to dare to appea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>irreligiouſly</hi> in the ſight of them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have by a ſolemn and ſacred Vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:99495:22"/> engaged
themſelves in a contrary Profeſſion. For as in civil matters, to
<hi>conceal Treaſon</hi> includes an equal guilt, and is obnoxious to the
ſame puniſhment with the <hi>actual offence:</hi> So in this caſe alſo,
he that does not <hi>reprehend</hi> a ſinner, is little leſs than a
cringing <hi>aſſiſtant</hi> to anothers debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery. For ſhame
therefore, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, let it not be ſaid of you, that you love the Society
of wicked Wretches, better than the bleſſed Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of Angels; and
that you had rather hear your <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Saviour</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, than
diſturb your helliſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: and will hazard the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your
ſouls, out of <hi>Courtſhip to the Devil,</hi> rather than be counted
abſurd among <hi>unreaſonable men.</hi> It was this filled the ſoul of
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> with amazement and horrour, if the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conſtrue him
right: <hi>Woe unto me,</hi> ſaith that generous Seer, <hi>becauſe I am a
man of unclean lips:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 6.5.</note> He cannot
praiſe God with the ſinging Seraphim, ſaith <hi>Jerom,</hi> becauſe his
lips are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, and their foulneſs aroſe from hence, that they had not
faithfully <hi>reproved</hi> wicked <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah.</hi> All <hi>Ely</hi>'s
perſonal holineſs is eclipſed with the <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99495:23"/> guilt of
thoſe hainous Tranſgreſſions he winked at.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> exhibits a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt a
ſort of Prieſts, <hi>Canni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals rather,</hi> that <hi>eat up the ſins of
the people:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.8.</note> for as the Viands we eat,
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſhort digeſtion become our own fleſh and blood; ſo the
<hi>Sins</hi> of the people which we <hi>ſmother</hi> and <hi>palliate,</hi>
being thus ſwallowed, become our <hi>own.</hi> The ſacred Miniſters of
Juſtice, in what Orb ſoever they ſhine, will eaſily apprehend how much
this Leſſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns them, eſpecially in this diſmal Juncture of
publick affairs; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me (not as an imperious Dictator, but) as an
humble Suppliant, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntreat you to
remember that the <hi>ſins</hi> of <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> which you labour not
within your powers to <hi>prevent,</hi> are <hi>yours</hi> in the guilt, as
well as thoſe of your own <hi>perſonal</hi> commiſſion: and the
exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Lenity in grand Enormities, brings a <hi>woe</hi> upon your own
heads <hi>For to juſtifie the Wicked, and condemn the Righteous, are both
alike to God</hi> Have a care therefore, you earthly gods, that you give no
<hi>Indulgence</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Countenance</hi> to that <hi>generation of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> that would be
poyſoning the <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99495:23"/> Cups of <hi>ſacred Monarchs,</hi> and
thruſting their ſtings into the innocent hearts of <hi>merciful
Princes,</hi> or ſucking the Royal blood of their <hi>lawful Soveraigns.</hi>
And as you have any love or regard for that Religion <hi>which is pure and
peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, truly Antient, Catholick and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick;</hi> or any abhorrency
to that inchanting City fully of Idolatry, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Blaſphemy; any
concern for the ſafety of his <hi>Majeſties Perſon,</hi> Crown and
Dignity, and your own <hi>Freedom</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> that you would
<hi>vex thoſe Midianites that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with their wiles;</hi> and correct
thoſe <hi>Amalekites</hi> which conſpire the ruine of our
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> and endeavour once more to make <hi>England,
Iſſachar</hi> like, <hi>couch under the burden of a Romiſh or Phanatick
Vaſſalage,</hi> 'Tis as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt as the Sun on the Meridian, that the
miſchief, intended is acted with <hi>two hands,</hi> (as the Prophet moſt
em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically), <hi>the beſt of which is a Bry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the moſt righteous
of them ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per than a Thorn-hedge;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mic. 3.4.</note>
which gives us cauſe to implore the aſſiſtance of both arms againſt
them, the ſtrength of the <hi>Brachium ſeculare,</hi> to be added to our
weaker <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> coertions, <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99495:24"/> to manacle
thoſe mighty men in <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious Wickedneſs,</hi> who every where
confront not us, but God, in <hi>open</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion or <hi>private</hi>
Treachery, in a <hi>Conclave</hi> or a <hi>Conventicle.</hi> Doth the Sun in
his imagined Progreſs meet with Conſtellations full of venome and
irregularity? their hurtful malice is corrected by his beneficial Raies: Doth
he meet with benign and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Planets? they have ſtrength and influence
added to them by that Superiour Light. What do we look for from the
<hi>Superiour Powers,</hi> but the approbation &amp; encouragement of the
virtuous Stars, and the <hi>Cure</hi> and <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> of the
Malignant? And here I cannot but complain of thoſe <hi>Stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks</hi>
that ſtop the courſe of Juſtice; Our Conſtables Aſſize and
Seſſion <hi>blanks,</hi> and our Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens Viſitation
<hi>bilks:</hi> Oh abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble partiality! they that are alwaies
<hi>inveighing</hi> againſt the <hi>Times,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge the petulancy of
a <hi>miſtaken Zeal;</hi> and come forth <hi>all the year</hi> with eager
Complaints againſt thoſe that ſit at the <hi>Helm;</hi> they that are
<hi>daily</hi> bellowing out their <hi>Diſcontents,</hi> and
<hi>arraigning</hi> their Governours failings; <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99495:24"/> they that
find all things amiſs in the management of <hi>publick affairs;</hi> when
themſelves are <hi>inſpected</hi> (and it lies in their <hi>power</hi> and
<hi>office,</hi> by virtue of the <hi>ſolemn Oath of God,</hi> to redreſs
theſe grievances, by preſenting the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the cognizance of their
Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours) like ſurly <hi>Elephants</hi> endure no repreſentment of their
uglineſs, not the leaſt aſperſion of a diſorder. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the
<hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> they will tell you nothing is
<hi>right;</hi> but on their own <hi>dunghills,</hi> in their own
<hi>Pariſhes,</hi> or <hi>Conſtableries, omnia bene,</hi> all is as it
ſhould be. Thus theſe poor <hi>Officers</hi> plunge themſelves into
<hi>Perjury,</hi> for fear of ſome <hi>frowning Sir;</hi> and <hi>diſoblige
their Conſciences, becauſe they will not diſpleaſe their
Neighbours;</hi> and by concealing <hi>paſt offences,</hi> bring them into a
<hi>cuſtome,</hi> which no vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance can remove. <hi>Voe ſilenti,</hi> woe
to the <hi>ſilent Tongue</hi> by whom the offence comes.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, And now <hi>Calumny</hi> follows with her mouth full of
Poyſon, ready to blaſt and <hi>offend</hi> all. As <hi>Timothies</hi> Pipe
enkindled the rage of the figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Macedonians,</hi> ſo ſpleen and
hatred are ſtirred up, with the rayling ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99495:25"/> of a
malevolent Tongue. The ſpies of <hi>Canaan,</hi> as an honeſt Rabbin
obſerves, did but diſcredit the trees and the ground, and the
ſtone-walls, and a thouſand miſchiefs enſued: how many evills may we
then think do they bring on <hi>themſelves</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> who
ſharpen their tongues to <hi>wound</hi> and <hi>diſgrace</hi> men! When our
Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ask'd his Diſciples <hi>what men were wont to ſay of him,</hi> had
they been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the vice of <hi>raiſing quarrels,</hi> they might a
reply'd, One calls you <hi>a Demoniac,</hi> another a <hi>Samaritan,</hi>
ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <hi>Wine-bibber;</hi> theſe are the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Characters you get
from a thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs people: But theſe harſh and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious titles are
kept from his ear; they tell him nothing but their good words; One calls you
<hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> another <hi>Jeremy,</hi> another ſome <hi>great
Prophet.</hi> The lips of Chriſts Spouſe are like a thread of Scarlet; yea,
indeed, like that Scarlet thread which <hi>Rahab</hi> tyed to her window, not
to ſtrangle any, but ſave all. The lips of a true Chriſtian are tyed with
ſuch threads as prevent miſchief, but breed none. It would be well done of
our ſhrill Dames, and imperious <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99495:25"/> Women, to think a little
on <hi>Rahab,</hi> and keep their houſes unhurt with the Scarlet thread of
<hi>ſilence</hi> and <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty.</hi> We ſhould not then have our ears
fill'd, and our hearts wounded with <hi>domeſtical brauls;</hi> we ſhould
not have <hi>groundleſs</hi> and <hi>rancorous tales</hi> ſo currant among
us; we ſhould not have every <hi>ſmall ſpark</hi> made a mountain of
<hi>Aetna,</hi> if this Scarlet thread of <hi>Silent and Modeſty Charity</hi>
were but religiouſly faſtned to <hi>the door of our lips.</hi> But
<hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Good</hi> men, for ought I ſee, are as ready to
over-laſh, as that <hi>weak Sex;</hi> and let me tell them, ſuch offences
are worſt. A ball of wool or leather hurts not where it lights; but a bullet
ſpit with violence from the mouth of a Canon, cauſes Towers and Bulwarks to
moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into duſt: So men of <hi>gravity</hi> being once heard to bolt out
<hi>raſh</hi> and <hi>unjuſt Verdicts,</hi> the <hi>weak</hi> Chriſtians
that cannot <hi>judge</hi> muſt needs <hi>ſtumble.</hi> How hath the
<hi>canker'd</hi> mouths of ſome demure <hi>Levites,</hi> who had firſt got
a reputation of ſingular Sanctity, blaſted the face and form of our
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Church, inſlam'd peoples hearts with a rude and ſpightful
Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion <pb n="42" facs="tcp:99495:26"/> of the <hi>Reverend Prelates</hi> ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
them! How have theſe <hi>great Wheels</hi> ſet the leſſer a going, that
now too many Families are become houſes of Inquiſition, when every
<hi>Notch'd Ideot</hi> will as freely as falſly talk of thoſe men, in
whoſe <hi>aweful pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> 'twould be ſawcineſs for them to
ſpeak at all without <hi>permiſſion.</hi> The <hi>Bible</hi> theſe holy
Railers ſeem to hug, hath told them, if a Ruler be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd, <hi>a bird of
the air</hi> (which <hi>Hugo</hi> the Cardinal thinks is an evil ſpirit)
<hi>ſhall accuſe them of it;</hi> and that if they inure their Tongues
<hi>to ſpeak evil of Dignities, and deſpiſe Dominions,</hi> they are
<hi>filthy dreamers,</hi> not true Diſciples. Our Lord hath put caſes of an
<hi>offending eye, and hand, and foot,</hi> but we hear nothing of an
offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding head; That, ſays <hi>Cajetan, challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth more regard, than to be
prophan'd by any vulgar breath, or to be cenſured by any thing under
Heaven.</hi> How much then they are to be reproved, that in their
<hi>Conventicles</hi> ſet their lungs to <hi>ſale</hi> to encourage
Sedition, and <hi>promote a new Rebellion by juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laſt;</hi> I
leave it to God and their own Conſciences to judge: but <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99495:26"/>
it makes me very ſuſpitious they are of the ſame ſpirit with
<hi>Diotrephes;</hi> (for there is a ſtrange temptation in being a Head, or
Ruler, though but of a Faction) and that their conſtant bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſuch
malicious words, diſloyal glances, and uncharitable reflections againſt
their lawful Superiours, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from that ambitious love they have to
Preheminence; which ſlains their Zeal with ſuch an averſion to thoſe
Humilities and due Submiſſion they owe to others.</p>
            <p>Methinks 'tis miſchief enough in the <hi>buſie tales of
Detraction,</hi> that ill opinions are bred by it, Unkindneſs foſter'd,
Charity quenched, and Jarrs raiſed that many times end in Blood, that we need
not add to it the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of an enraged Deity. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells
us, <hi>There are ſix things the Lord hates, and the ſeventh he counts a
foul abomination.</hi> Pride and Bloodineſs, and wicked Imaginations, were
hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough; but there is yet a worſe, a more abominable thing, <hi>a
ſcandalous Babler,</hi> a ſower of Diſcord among brethren: this ſhall
be laid in our diſh in that terrible Judgment, that we ſat like grim
Judges, and ſpake <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99495:27"/> harſhly againſt our brother,
<hi>and ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our mothers ſon.</hi> This is a fruitful, though a
fooliſh Vice. For through the help of the Devil, and our corrupt Nature,
whenſoever we have a mind to throw dirt at one another, there is enough to be
found in every ſtreet. The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>In ſome things we offend
all.</hi> Which renders it the greaſt imprudence imaginable, for him that
hath a houſe made of glaſs, to throw ſtones at his neighbours windows,
when the ſlighteſt requital will quickly demoliſh the brittle Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of
his own Reputation. 
<q> 
                  <l>Alterius dictum aut factum ne carpſeris unquam</l> 
                  <l>Exemplo ſimili ne te derideat alter.</l>
               </q> And however we
ſet a <hi>grave</hi> look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, as if we had done nothing amiſs;
however our own <hi>Oracles</hi> pleaſe us; however we riſe up from our
gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulous Bench, forgetting the miſchief is done both to the
<hi>audience</hi> and <hi>accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> Yet the ſevere Judge of Heaven and
Earth will call us to a ſtrict account, and make us at laſt ſee the
foulneſs of that Vice we accounted <pb n="45" facs="tcp:99495:27"/> none; and then
<hi>voe detrahenti, Wo be to that man by whoſe detracting tongue the offence
comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, Pernicious counſels are <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences</hi> of the
Tongue alſo, and as groſs and ſpreading as any. Sin is then grown to a
fearful height, when it delights to ſpread its infection; when the leud man
takes up his ſeat in <hi>the Chair of Peſtilence;</hi> when like a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
of the Chair, thoſe evils that he practiſeth himſelf, he ſeeks to teach
others. The Spirit of God finds fault with the <hi>Church of Pregamus,</hi>
that ſhe had a ſort of men that held the <hi>Doctrine of Balaam;</hi> upon
the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of which, ſome will think, ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi> there were
ſome in St. <hi>Judes</hi> time that ſtudied the Black Art, ſome profound
Wizzards that pretended the hidden skill of that old Serpent. No, that man
teacheth the Doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> that follows his example in
perſwading unwary ſouls to the commiſſion of ſcandalous Actions. It
was <hi>Balaams</hi> bad counſel, that laid the fair women of <hi>Moab</hi>
as <hi>ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks</hi> before the People of God. Seducing
perſwaſions, which either <hi>ſtumble</hi> us in the waies of
<hi>Goodneſs,</hi> or <pb n="46" facs="tcp:99495:28"/> lead us into a <hi>vitious
courſe,</hi> (and ſo pull the wrath of God on our heads) theſe are the
Doctrines of <hi>Balaam.</hi> Thus the Serpent ſeduced <hi>Eve,</hi> and
ſhe <hi>Adam:</hi> Thus <hi>Solomons</hi> wives turn his heart from God, and
crafty <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> puts Inceſt into <hi>Abſolons</hi> head: Thus a
<hi>litigious</hi> wretch that hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done himſelf in Suits of <hi>Law,</hi>
lies like a gloing coal ready to <hi>kindle</hi> others; for <hi>none proves a
deeper knave, than a ſpent fool.</hi> Thus the corrupted Advocate puts
<hi>Lies</hi> and <hi>Perjury</hi> into his <hi>Clyents</hi> mouth, for the
mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of an <hi>unjuſt</hi> Cauſe. Thus furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Revengers</hi>
bring in Seconds, to embrue their hands in blood: Thus Country-<hi>Tiplers</hi>
are grown <hi>Raſhers</hi> and <hi>Anchova</hi>'s to one another: Thus one
<hi>Sacrilegious</hi> Cormorant, the Bell-weather of the Pariſh, encourages
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and he a third, to a <hi>conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Churches
due!</hi> How fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and lamentable is it to conceive what a deal of this
<hi>ſcandalous Ware</hi> is openly vended in City and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try! How the
gripple <hi>Shopman</hi> nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures his Apprentice in a Trade of <hi>Lyes:</hi>
how the ravenous <hi>Cheater</hi> draws on his landed <hi>Novice</hi> to
<hi>Dice</hi> 
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:99495:28"/> and <hi>Drabs:</hi> How one cries out with
<hi>Solomons</hi> Ruffler, <hi>Come, let us take our ſill of love till the
day break:</hi> another, <hi>Come, let us lay wait for blood:</hi> another,
<hi>Let us lurk privately to undo the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; let us joyn purſes, and find
out the ſtrong drink, and continue till night at the wine-boles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How would the King take it, ſhould <hi>War</hi> and
<hi>Tumul</hi> ariſe, to have his own <hi>Guard</hi> enticed from
<hi>him,</hi> to ſerve on the Enemies <hi>ſide!</hi> we are by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm
become of the <hi>houſhold</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue of God, and ſhall we make it
our ſtudie to pluck his <hi>Servants</hi> away from him, to corrupt his
<hi>houſhold</hi> with traiterous counſels, and perſwade them to ſerve
on his <hi>Enemies</hi> ſide, and not look for a furious revenge, not ſo
much as a rebuke from our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters mouth? Truly 'twould be well-pleaſing
to us, that we might alwaies come to you as the gracious <hi>Heralds of
Peace:</hi> But Chriſt Jeſus hath given us an example, to <hi>thunder</hi>
in ſuch a Caſe as this, to ring it <hi>aloud</hi> in the terrible
<hi>Ruffians</hi> ear, <hi>Voe male conſulenti, Wo be to the man by whoſe
pernicious counſel the offence comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99495:29"/>Seventhly, How have I forgot that
<hi>tempting</hi> Syren, whoſe enchanting Songs lulls <hi>incautious</hi>
Marriners in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſound ſleep, while their Veſſel ſplits upon a Rock!
That crafty <hi>Panther,</hi> whoſe odoriferous breath enticeth herds of
Cattel after him to their own deſtruction; I mean the <hi>ſmooth and
flattering Tongue, by which the Offence comes.</hi> As the Shell-fiſh is
mounted aloſt in the Eagles Pounces, to be ſhattered with the greater fall:
So frail men are highly extol'd by their <hi>pick-thanks,</hi> but 'tis to
tumble them down into a depth of Sin. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious balms of ungodly men have a
ſecret doſe of Poyſon in the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that <hi>Oleum peccati</hi>
&amp; <hi>Oleum vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> are uſed promiſcuouſly in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew
Dialect. Now as dogs purſue their game beſt, when the huntſman excites
them to ſport and courage with his voice: ſo wicked men run more
<hi>eagerly</hi> into vitious courſes, when they are <hi>encouraged</hi> to
it by their <hi>obſequious Flatterers.</hi> 'Tis now nick-nam'd a poynt of
<hi>good Manners,</hi> a token of <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Gentleneſs,</hi>
to ſooth and applaud men in Vice and Vanity: and he that baſely 
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99495:29"/> ſtoops not to thoſe <hi>inhumane applian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi>
ſhall be reported Proud, Peeviſh, and Envious. But know your
<hi>friends,</hi> know your <hi>enemies</hi> better, whoſoever you are that
love to be <hi>tickled</hi> with the gloſing tongues of
<hi>paraſitical</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers. To ſteal our Houſhold-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion
were a groſs theft; but to be rob'd of our Seed-corn, was a worſe damage.
What are our inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but <hi>ſeminaries</hi> of all the
goodneſs can be derived from us? Now theſe affections are <hi>ſtol'n</hi>
and <hi>ſpoyl'd,</hi> when <hi>oily</hi> tongues, to <hi>endear
themſelves,</hi> &amp; patch up the <hi>rents</hi> in <hi>tat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd</hi>
fortunes, ſhall ſo egregiouſly <hi>abuſe</hi> us, as to think well of
our own <hi>enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and purſue what we ſhould moſt abhor. What
can miſchief us more, than the <hi>pilfering of our hearts,</hi> and
<hi>depraving our inclinations?</hi> for by this means the very Seeds of Grace
are riſled away, and we are left barren (like the Fig-tree) to the curſe of
an incenſed Judge. <hi>Woe be to them that call good evil, and evil good;
that put light for darkneſs, and darkneſs for light.</hi> Vae Adulanti,
<hi>woe to the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Tongue by which the offence comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99495:30"/>Eighthly, And may we not rank thoſe in the
Liſt of <hi>Vocal Offenders,</hi> from whoſe <hi>unſavoury Jeſts,
laſcivious Songs,</hi> and <hi>ſcurrilous Pens,</hi> balls of Wild-fire are
caſt abroad to inflame others; whoſe Bills, like tame Ducks, are ever
dabling in ſtinking mud? How is our <hi>tuneful Melody</hi> ſcandaliz'd
with <hi>debauch'd Airs;</hi> the harmleſs recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ative Inſtruments of
Muſick, trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd into the Engines of Miſchief, our
<hi>entertainments</hi> fly-blown with and looſe and abuſive Catches! I
hope none will be ſo uncharitable to think I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all under
<hi>Offences</hi> that <hi>muſically</hi> recreate <hi>themſelves,</hi> and
delight <hi>others;</hi> no, for <hi>Gods people</hi> may be <hi>merry</hi>
within the limits of <hi>filial duty:</hi> 'tis the <hi>abuſe</hi> onely that
I declaim againſt, who am of <hi>Ariſtippus</hi>'s mind: 
<q> 
                  <l>In libri Patris Sacris,</l> 
                  <l>Mens quae pudica eſt neſciet corrumpier.</l>
               </q> But
theſe empty ſounds vaniſh into Air, and reach but to few; we have found a
way, with the publication of <hi>obſcene Pamphlets,</hi> to make our
<hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> Eternal, and are become univerſal Bauds to the whole
world. <hi>Cupid</hi> is <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99495:30"/> Crown'd a <hi>Laureat,</hi> and
that unchaſt <hi>licenſe</hi> which hath been expung'd and
<hi>hiſs'd</hi> at in <hi>Heathen Poets,</hi> is hug'd and applauded in
Chriſtian. The Jews have a ſaying, that when Scurrility is heard without,
the door rots; the door! nay, the Audience rather; for <hi>rotten communication
is the quickest cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupter of good Manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can we think Almighty God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd our <hi>breath</hi> on us to
no other purpoſe, but to blaſt his Image? Can we think our Creator intended
us for nothing elſe, but to be the Devils bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows? Oh woful
<hi>merriment,</hi> that <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts</hi> our God, and <hi>grieves</hi> his
Spirit and holy Angels, to make <hi>ſport</hi> for the <hi>Devil</hi> and his
<hi>infernal Crew!</hi> Let <hi>no evil commnication,</hi> ſaith the holy
Apoſtle, <hi>proceed from you mouth;</hi> and preſently adds, <hi>Grieve
not the Spirit of God.</hi> Go now, unhappy <hi>drols,</hi> and think to
delight your <hi>fond</hi> admirers with an <hi>obſcene Jeſt:</hi> but
remember, that truly Religious hearts are griev'd; nay, the Spirit of God is
<hi>griev'd</hi> with thoſe that thus <hi>hazzard their ſouls,</hi> to
purchaſe the reputation of <hi>Facetious Blateroons.</hi> Hath Chriſt
pronounc'd <hi>weeping</hi> and <hi>woe</hi> to them that <hi>laugh 
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:99495:31"/> now:</hi> How then can they think to eſcape, that do not
only <hi>admit,</hi> but <hi>cauſe</hi> and <hi>further</hi> this vain and
frolick exceſs. Oh lamentable and heedleſs <hi>folly!</hi> to kindle a
<hi>wanton</hi> delight in ſome <hi>looſe heart,</hi> to feed a
<hi>laſcivious ear,</hi> and make our company <hi>merry,</hi> we bring on our
ſouls a <hi>ſorrowful woe. Voe turpiloqui, woe to the ſcurrilous Tongue
by whom the offence comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, Deriſion and Mockage is the laſt <hi>offence</hi> I
ſhall arraign in the Tongue: For, <hi>O fooliſh</hi> Galatians, <hi>who
hath bewitched you!</hi> ſaith the choſen Veſſel. As the grumbled Charm
of a Witch, ſome think will ſtrike dead a little child, ſo the goodneſs
of a weak Chriſtian, with every breath of deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is almoſt blaſted.
How little a thing ſtaies a boat on the river, and ſtartles a horſe by
the way-ſide! no leſs eaſily are we deter'd in a courſe of Goodneſs.
Some frail <hi>diſordered</hi> man hath the ſymptomes of a growing
<hi>Cure</hi> upon his Soul, has mew'd off his ſick feathers, and now begins
to <hi>ſtartle</hi> at his former <hi>exceſs;</hi> to forbear his
<hi>brain-ſhaking Cups,</hi> and <hi>hell-invented Oaths;</hi> has ty'd up
his Tongue to the <hi>good behaviour,</hi> and impoſed on his 
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99495:31"/> Converſation the ſtrict Rules of Religion: and now the
<hi>fleering</hi> drunkards make Songs upon him; the <hi>ſcorns</hi> and
<hi>taunts</hi> of his old <hi>Mates</hi> lie in his way, and he <hi>falls</hi>
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain upon the ſame <hi>rock of offence.</hi> Another is <hi>mildly
diſpos'd,</hi> and would wink at a wrong, but <hi>hot-ſpurs</hi> are
hiſſing his <hi>puſillanimity;</hi> he ſhall be mark't out for a
<hi>Coward</hi> and <hi>Milk-ſop,</hi> that dares not incur the guilt of a
ſpontaneous <hi>Murder,</hi> to gratifie ſome beaſtly humour. Should a
ſort of poor <hi>Chriſtians</hi> be redeem'd from the <hi>Turkiſh
Gallyes,</hi> what would we think of him that ſhould endeavour to
<hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray</hi> them again to their old <hi>ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes?</hi> Is a ſoul
<hi>looſed</hi> from the power of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Satan,</hi> what a
<hi>horrid villany</hi> is it to enſnare it again into that
<hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity!</hi> Whoſoever he be, that thus nips the <hi>buddings</hi> of
Grace, like the cruel <hi>Egyptians,</hi> he does but ſtrangle the Hebrew
Babes that God would have preſerved; and like Tyrannous <hi>Herod,</hi> put
Chriſt to death, when he is firſt <hi>conceived</hi> and born in a
regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate heart. But the moſt <hi>degenerate</hi> ſort of
<hi>ſcoffers,</hi> and <hi>dregs</hi> of mankind, are thoſe that
<hi>ſcoff at Religion,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99495:32"/> our hopes of
<hi>another Life,</hi> as the Phantaſms of a melancholy <hi>Priest,</hi> or
the Politick ſtratagems of ſome cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Stateſmen, to keep people in
awe. We are caſt into the very <hi>Dog-daies</hi> of Atheiſm and
Ungodlineſs, and live among thoſe which ſcoff at ſuch things that are
moſt <hi>Sacred</hi> and to be <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> at. Oh the frequent
<hi>darings</hi> of <hi>Divine</hi> Vengeance, that continually pierces our
<hi>ears,</hi> and wounds our <hi>hearts!</hi> and thoſe vented in ſuch
<hi>direful expreſſions, that the moſt deeply damned in hell could never
be guilty of worſer.</hi> Wonder not if this be the <hi>Cordolium</hi> of all
that are religiouſly ſenſible in the land, if it puts them into the
weeping Prophets <hi>Iliaca paſſio, My bowels, my bowels, I am pain'd at
the very heart;</hi> for 'tis enough to raiſe a <hi>paroxyſm</hi> of grief
and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the holy Apoſtle, and make the <hi>hearts</hi> of good
men <hi>ſink</hi> and <hi>dye</hi> in them, to ſee how
<hi>prodigiouſly</hi> leud and impudent men are grown. Yea, thoſe <hi>dull
ſouls</hi> who are inſipid and dreggy on all other arguments, are by the
<hi>Devils,</hi> and the <hi>Leviathans</hi> help, grown eloquent in
<hi>abuſing God</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> to magnifie their abus'd 
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:99495:32"/> 
               <hi>Corpuſcularean</hi> Philoſophy.</p>
            <p>Tell them of a <hi>God,</hi> and they laugh aloud at your folly,
who are ſo <hi>tame</hi> and <hi>childiſh</hi> to believe what you
<hi>never ſaw;</hi> and pitty your <hi>ignorance,</hi> for being deluded by
the <hi>men in black,</hi> into the <hi>melancholy</hi> thoughts of
<hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Democritus</hi> and <hi>Epicurus</hi> are polite Authors, and in
better credit with ſuch, than <hi>Moſes,</hi> St. <hi>John,</hi> or St.
<hi>Paul;</hi> and <hi>Hobs</hi>'s borrowed Hypotheſis, than the ſacred
Volumes of the Old and New Teſtament. 
<q>Quis fando temperet à lachrimis?</q> They can ſolve the
<hi>Phoenomena</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> without the allowance of a
<hi>Deity;</hi> and derive the <hi>worlds</hi> Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal from a <hi>Fortuitous
concourſe of Atomes.</hi> Thus theſe imperious <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theistical</hi>
Dictators, boaſt themſelves the only men of <hi>Learning</hi> and
<hi>Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> ſtigmatizing all others, as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Ruſticks, and
illiterate Buffoon's, that have nothing of <hi>generoſity,</hi> who dare not
ſet their mouths againſt <hi>Heaven,</hi> and defie the Authority of their
<hi>Maker.</hi> Now to blunt the edge of this <hi>ſcoffing Wit,</hi> which
boaſts of ſo <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99495:33"/> eaſie a <hi>Victory</hi> over
<hi>deſpiſed Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> Pray conſider, that their onely
argument is taken from <hi>Senſe,</hi> unleſs they enforce them with
<hi>Oaths,</hi> the uſual Graces and Ornaments, and the only <hi>proof</hi>
they have for ſuch <hi>wild diſcourſes;</hi> and are to be pitied and
pray'd for, but not <hi>diſputed</hi> with, leſt we ſpread the
<hi>contagion,</hi> having to do with ſuch as had rather <hi>looſe
Heaven,</hi> than live <hi>ſoberly;</hi> and have no other reaſon why the
ſay there is no God, but becauſe 'twould be well for them there was none.
'Tis a ſtrange de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion that hath infatuated theſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd Animals,
that they dare ſport with the flames of Hell, in ſcoffing at God and
Goodneſs, and the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>ſtartle</hi> at their own
<hi>Shadow,</hi> frighted with the noiſe of <hi>Thunder,</hi> and are as
fearful of being <hi>alone</hi> in the night, as other <hi>vermine</hi> are of
light and company. 
<q>O quam multos dominos habet, qui unum non habet!</q> Every
ſurprizing accident <hi>skares</hi> them from their <hi>Principles;</hi>
there being nothing more evident, than that the <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99495:33"/> greateſt
Atheiſt is alwaies the moſt notorious Coward. Thus we read of
<hi>Antiochus,</hi> when he enjoyed the conſtant ſeries of a ſmiling
fortune, boaſted himſelf <hi>Superiour to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;</hi> but when the
inconſtant Goddeſs withdrew her Beams, and appear'd unto him under a cloud
of Troubles, he chang'd his note; for having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a fall out of his
Chariot, and his inſolency curb'd by an immediate blow from Heaven, he could
ſay then, as too many of our <hi>Atheiſts</hi> do upon the aſſault of a
<hi>diſeaſe,</hi> and the fears of death <hi>(Pray God it be not then too
late)</hi> 
               <q>Juſtum eſt hominem mortalem ſubditum eſſe Deo.</q>
               <hi>It is meet and requiſite for mortal men to be ſubject to the immortal
God.</hi> Tell me, I pray you, that pretend to be ſo great maſters of
Reaſon, whether 'tis not more agreeable to the principles of right Reaſon,
to believe a <hi>God,</hi> than deny it; if ſo, then give over (ye men of
ſenſe) thoſe ſordid extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, that render you <hi>Clowns</hi> to
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. <hi>Burlesk</hi> no more upon God, <pb n="58" facs="tcp:99495:34"/> nor caſt
diſgrace upon the <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>bleſſed Trinity:</hi> For if
frail man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted of infirmities is ſo jealous of his <hi>Honour,</hi>
that (by the commands of Hell) he thinks himſelf oblig'd to <hi>duel</hi> him
that ſtains it; How will God Almighty be jealous in taking
<hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> againſt ſuch as blaſpheme his <hi>Godhead,</hi>
neglect their own <hi>Salvation,</hi> and chooſe rather to venture their
whole <hi>Happineſs</hi> in gratifying their corruptions, than provide for
their own <hi>Safety</hi> by examining their <hi>groundleſs
ſurmiſes?</hi> And <hi>you that have better learned Chriſt,</hi> be
intreated t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhun the Society of
ſuch <hi>ſcoffing A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts,</hi> who would <hi>laugh</hi> you into
<hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal mourning,</hi> and mock you from the exerciſe of Piety, till the
Dev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>claim</hi> you by
<hi>Preſcription.</hi> By <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
ſtratagem or device hath the Devil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> much <hi>diſheartned</hi> from <hi>Religion,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>afflicted</hi> men for it, as by
<hi>Scoffers,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make
themſelves the main promote<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of
his <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and advancers of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Kingdom:</hi> by no <hi>methods</hi> hath th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Devil more <hi>inſtructed</hi>
thoſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would be bad, and
<hi>diſcouraged</hi> other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from
being <hi>good,</hi> than by theſe <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed</hi> inſtruments of
Cruelty. Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:99495:34"/>
the Jews could not withſtand the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous coming of the
<hi>Meſſias</hi> any other way, they took ſhelter in a <hi>taunting
proverb, Can any good come out of Nazareth?</hi> When the convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing power of
<hi>Miracles</hi> had proclaim'd his <hi>Divinity,</hi> and <hi>the Works that
Chriſt did had declar'd he was the Son of God,</hi> they had no way to
prevent believing on him, but <hi>Is not this the Carpenters Son?</hi> Thus
alſo fares it with <hi>Religion,</hi> that they who have their minds
<hi>eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> from it, from thence take an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to
<hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>deride</hi> it. But if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can perſwade
you to riſe out of <hi>the Chair of Peſtilence;</hi> See the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of
Gods <hi>Judgments</hi> upon <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: Iſhmael</hi> mocking
<hi>Iſaac,</hi> was <hi>bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi> the pleaſant land, and expoſed
as a prey to forreigners: <hi>Michal</hi> mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>David</hi> for dancing
before the <hi>Ark,</hi> was puniſhed with the <hi>ſorrow</hi> &amp;
ſhame of <hi>barrenneſs. Machivel</hi> that mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Atheiſt,</hi>
dyed in the priſon of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;</hi> and <hi>Julian</hi> that made
<hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity a deriſion,</hi> expired in a moſt hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and
<hi>cruel</hi> manner. Nothing is more juſt and equitable, than for the
<hi>impudent</hi> in ſin, to be <hi>daſhed</hi> out of
<hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,</hi> and to be beaten with their <pb n="60" facs="tcp:99495:35"/>
               <hi>own</hi> Weapons; for <hi>the Lord ſcorneth the ſcorners,</hi> and will
mock at their Calamities when they come, who mock'd at God before they was
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted: take heed therefore you <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend none of God's little ones,</hi>
thoſe that begin to <hi>tast</hi> ſweetneſs in the <hi>Word of God,</hi>
and the promiſes of the <hi>world</hi> to come; but rather ſtrengthen the
<hi>weak</hi> hands, and the <hi>feeble</hi> knees, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage all men in
the way of Goodneſs. But Changelings ſometimes paſs for the Babes of
Chriſt, and while I am pleading for the <hi>Righteous,</hi> I would not
patronize a <hi>counterfeit</hi> in the ways of <hi>malice</hi> and
<hi>diſobedience,</hi> in the ways of <hi>guilt</hi> and
<hi>diſſimulation,</hi> (which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny now take for the <hi>ſtreight
paths</hi> of Chriſt). I think we do well to ſtop your courſe, and to
<hi>deride</hi> your devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: but far be it from us to <hi>retard</hi> you
in the ways of <hi>Jeſus, the good old way wherein you may find life for your
Souls;</hi> the ways that are ſtrewed with <hi>Love, Peace, Meekneſs,</hi>
and <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility;</hi> woe be unto us if we call you not (as we do daily) to
walk therein: but if any by <hi>precept,</hi> or <hi>example,</hi> put you from
the purſuit of theſe real Graces, <hi>Voe deridenti, woe be to that 
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99495:35"/> man, by whoſe deriding Tongue the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next member that upon ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignment will be found guilty of
<hi>Offences,</hi> is the <hi>Eye;</hi> a part of the body endued with ſo
much <hi>excellency,</hi> and withal ſo much <hi>iniquity,</hi> that I know
not whether it may more invite your admiration or your ſorrow; for when the
<hi>heart</hi> corrupts the <hi>eye,</hi> and the eye betraies the heart, it
ſtains its own glory, by agreeing with the <hi>mind</hi> in the ſervice of
Iniquity; it renders the eye an egregious offender: for if with a
<hi>greedy</hi> aſpect it <hi>looks</hi> upon food, without charging the
ſtomach, 'tis guilty of <hi>Gluttony;</hi> if on a woman to <hi>lust</hi>
after her, 'tis guilty of <hi>Adultery;</hi> if it beholds riches with
<hi>covetous</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, it hath committed <hi>Robbery;</hi> if on
anothers <hi>good,</hi> with an eye of <hi>evil,</hi> it commits the ſin of
<hi>Envy;</hi> which is the meaning of our Saviours reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Is
thine eye evil, becauſe mine is good?</hi> But as if the vice of the
<hi>husband-men</hi> were transformed into a virtue, ſinful man is
continually <hi>reviving</hi> it, in repining that his <hi>fellow labourer</hi>
in the vineyard that came in late, ſhould receive <hi>equal</hi> wages with
himſelf, who <pb n="62" facs="tcp:99495:36"/> like <hi>Coeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi>
can endure no equal, nor ſecond to rival him in his victorious Atchievements:
Hence it is that Envy is called the <hi>green-ſickneſs of the Soul,</hi>
that feeding upon cinders, or rubbiſh, <hi>contracts the ſtature,</hi>
impallids the body to a <hi>hectick leanneſs,</hi> and through default of the
liver, ſpots the face with <hi>gutta Roſacea, as the effigies of the man by
whom the offence comes.</hi> This is he that cannot endure the abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of
any, ſhould be admitted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors with his <hi>feeble</hi> acquirements;
thinks illuſtrious <hi>merits</hi> an upbraiding his own <hi>defects,</hi>
and that he is lighted into envy by the ſplendour of his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals virtues,
againſt whom he hath no other quarrel, than what the <hi>Affricans</hi> have
againſt the Sun, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rit fulgore ſuo;</hi> or what one had againſt
<hi>Demoſthenes</hi>'s candle, onely becauſe it <hi>ſtood in his
light.</hi> This ſin of <hi>Envy</hi> renders men more vitious than
<hi>devils;</hi> for we no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where read, that they envy one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Beſides,
their malice ariſeth from the want of that good which they have loſt, and
theſe envy that good which another hath found. And now through the
ſuggeſtions of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> the ſinner wracks himſelf with 
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:99495:36"/> jealouſies and ſurmiſes, to perſwade himſelf
each <hi>Candidate</hi> is his enemy, that he hath a greater ſhare in the
love of the <hi>Popularity;</hi> and this puts him upon <hi>baſe and
ungenerous employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> to ſatisfie an <hi>unreaſonable</hi> and
<hi>impatient jealouſie;</hi> ſends him as a <hi>ſpy</hi> into every dark
corner, to diſcover that which only dwells in his own <hi>imagination;</hi>
and all this while he hath perhaps been fighting with his own <hi>Chagrene
Ghoſt,</hi> and hath had no other enemy, than his own ill nature. This makes
it a kind of <hi>miſery</hi> to be excellent, becauſe it is ſure to be
atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with <hi>malignity;</hi> it being the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant guiſe of
<hi>poorer ſpirits,</hi> thoſe <hi>brats of mouldy clay,</hi> to erect
obelisks to their own <hi>obſcure bearings,</hi> out of the <hi>ruines</hi>
of others: and ſince they are unable to raiſe themſelves to the eſteem
of their adverſaries, they endeavour by Calumny <hi>(or the exerciſe of
their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friended, not acquired authority)</hi> to bring them down to the
ſame ignoble level with themſelves. This is a ſtone of
<hi>Stumbling,</hi> and a rock of <hi>offence,</hi> for Chriſtians to malign
each other: 
<note place="margin">Joh. 1.2.9.</note>
               <hi>for he that hateth his
brother is in darkneſs until now; but he that loveth abideth 
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99495:37"/> in the light, and there is no occaſion of ſtumbling in
him.</hi> But that which aggravates the offence, and makes the ſin become
ſo <hi>exceſſively ſinful,</hi> is, that the only cauſe for which the
<hi>envious</hi> man is enraged againſt his brother, is that <hi>for
which</hi> Cain <hi>ſlew</hi> Abel, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his own works were evil,
and his brothers good.</hi> And that this hath been the conſtant practiſe
of this devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh vice, will appear when we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider, that for
this cauſe <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> brethren ſold him; and it was virtue in
<hi>David,</hi> that provoked <hi>Saul</hi> to ſeek his life; and the
<hi>Ninevites</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, that diſtempered <hi>Jonas;</hi> for this
cauſe (namely unparallel'd good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) 'twas, that the Jews conſpired the
death of our Saviour, and which made the Roman Governour endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour his
releaſement, becauſe he knew <hi>that for envy they had delivered him.</hi>
This is even the nature of envy, to aſſault the <hi>worthieſt</hi>
perſons, whoſe eminency ſhines beyond others in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Actions, but
meddles not with ſuch as be of meaner quality. But to perſwade men from the
practiſe of this unchriſtian and unmanlike vice, know, that Divine
Juſtice hath <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99495:37"/> appointed this ſin to be the torment of
it ſelf; for Envy, like cankered Braſs, feeds upon his own ſubſtance. 
<q> 
                  <l>Juſtius invidia nihil eſt, quae protinus ipſum</l> 
                  <l>Authorem rodit excrutiat<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>ſuum.</l>
               </q> But I ſhall
rather preſcribe <hi>Antidotes</hi> againſt this poyſon, than ſhew the
puniſhment that attends it: and to that purpoſe, if thou ſeeſt another
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in Learning, Judgment, or the like commendables, be not ſo envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
to thy ſelf, as to be vexed at that which may better or inform thee, if thou
wouldſt make a right uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>If thou hear him defend the <hi>Truth</hi> with applauſe of
others, let not a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe</hi> emulation tempt thee to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the
contrary, to the <hi>ſubverting</hi> of the hearers: for there is, ſaith
<hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen,</hi> a happineſs even to be <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.</hi> And it is far
better to be <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly</hi> vanquiſhed, and quit the field, than to
obtain an inglorious <hi>Victory,</hi> with the ſhipwrack of true Religion.
If thou ſee another endued with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Graces, as <hi>Virtue,
Knowledge, <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99495:38"/> Temperance, Patience;</hi> here is matter for
thy <hi>godly</hi> Emulation, but not for thy bitter Envying: thou ſhouldſt
ſtrive to <hi>match</hi> him in the exerciſe of holy duties, but not to
damp his ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity by malitious detraction. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Saviours precept,
<hi>our light ſhould ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing our good
Works, may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven.</hi> Therefore let not thy
envy be the cloud to <hi>dim</hi> the light of anothers works, and thereby
hinder ſo much <hi>glory,</hi> as might redound to thy heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 
<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> Although ſuch a man were
thy <hi>enemy,</hi> yet becauſe Almighty God is <hi>glorified</hi> by him, he
ought to be thy friend: and now becauſe God is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by him, ſhall he
therefore be thy <hi>enemy? God forbid!</hi> Remember whoſe work he is doing,
and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage his <hi>faint</hi> endeavours with the addition of thy
ſervice, and help to effect what thou dayly prayeſt for; That <hi>Gods will
may be done on Earth</hi> by thee, and thy fellow-ſervants, <hi>as it is in
Heaven</hi> by the glorious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
            <p>The Tongue is now <hi>wormed,</hi> and the <hi>Cataract of
Envy</hi> over the Eye is <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99495:38"/> touch'd; but I muſt lead you
on with <hi>Ezekiel</hi> to more abominations, to more offences in our lives;
they are of two ſorts, <hi>injurious</hi> and <hi>exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>injurious offences</hi> are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently
indigitated in our Saviours words: for who receiveth his <hi>little ones,</hi>
but their hopeful benefactors? and who on the other ſide gives them
<hi>offence,</hi> but their <hi>ſpiteful oppoſers?</hi> And here our old
Complainants are ready to commence their ſuit, in rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning up the hard
meaſures offered to their Zealous guides, who are exil'd their Pulpits,
ſtript of their Maintenance, rated, fined, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as their word is;
whereas the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is moſt evident, Being treated, through the kindneſs
of ſome, and the remiſneſs of others, more favourably than the Law
allows, and their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice deſerves. And when they fall under any pecuniary
mulct or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral reſtraint, <hi>their puniſhment is of themſelves;</hi>
they cannot be called <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Sufferers,</hi> but <hi>injurious
Agreſſors.</hi> I would to God they would once learn to ſaddle the right
Aſs: for, as St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaid of <hi>Sara</hi> and
<hi>Hagar,</hi> 
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99495:39"/> the Maid did more perſecute the
Miſtreſs by her <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>ſaucineſs,</hi> than the
Miſtreſs did her Maid by the <hi>ſeverity</hi> of her diſcipline: and
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Diſſenters clamorous Charge, upon a <hi>Melius
inquirendum,</hi> 'twill be found, that <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> do more
<hi>perſecute and offend the Church,</hi> than <hi>holy Church</hi> doth
perſecute or offend them: and ſo unhappy conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences have been the
iſſue of their lucrous ingannations, that the Church better endured the
<hi>Swords</hi> of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> than the tongues of
<hi>Schiſmaticks:</hi> for while we <hi>ſmarted,</hi> Unity remained; but
while theſe <hi>Anticeremonian Bigots</hi> are believed, the <hi>Church</hi>
is obnoxious to ruine, by the <hi>ſeeds of diviſion</hi> they ſowe
amongſt us.</p>
            <p>But that which ſpreads the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is, that the
Schiſmatical tenents of ſome <hi>Non-conforming</hi> brethren, like <hi>ill
weeds</hi> in a <hi>fat ſoil,</hi> have done greater miſchief through the
good opinion men have of their <hi>perſonal</hi> Sanctity. <hi>They are good
men!</hi> and (by a bad conſequence) <hi>all they do muſt be ſo
accounted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what can the <hi>pretence</hi> amount to, when examin'd by an
<hi>intelligent</hi> 
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:99495:39"/> and <hi>unprejudiced</hi> ſoul? for
'tis not flouriſhing the banner of <hi>goodneſs,</hi> that can priviledge
men from either errour or ſinning: neither ought the unreprovableneſs of
mens converſe in other things, countenance their <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi>
opinions, or <hi>Church-dividing</hi> practices, againſt the light of divine
Scripture, and right Reaſon. Let mens <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> be
as large as <hi>they themſelves</hi> would have it believed, muſt not men
of honeſty live under Laws, <hi>and ſubmit to every Ordinance of man for
the Lords ſake?</hi> Surely however they whiſper the contrary, they dare
not ſpeak it aloud, leſt they be as openly convicted <hi>to reſiſt the
Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, and purchaſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the gildings and varniſh of thoſe ſelfiſh
intrigues, whereby men of good hearts, but <hi>weak heads;</hi> and women, who
have <hi>weakeſt</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but <hi>ſtrongeſt wills and
paſſions,</hi> are cozened into a good opinion of theſe painted
out-ſides, to embrace a Cloud inſtead of <hi>Juno,</hi> and forſake a
<hi>peaceable Church,</hi> to be members of a <hi>contentious Conventicle.</hi>
I take no delight in ſearching the wounds, or <pb n="70" facs="tcp:99495:40"/>
diſplaying the faults of a religious Party; but in ſo noble a Cauſe
'twould be a ſin to hold my peace: <hi>Meam injuriam patienter tuli, injuriam
contra ſponſam Chriſti ferre non potui.</hi> 'Tis a <hi>deplorable
offence,</hi> that men of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent parts and improvements, which might be
eminently <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to the <hi>Church of God,</hi> ſhould
abuſe their <hi>lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> to the maintenance of a <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and
inſtead of winning ſouls to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, with <hi>buſie</hi> and
<hi>ill-boding</hi> diligence compaſs ſea and land to draw proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes to
a <hi>party.</hi> How many Kilns and Barns (the preſent threſhing-ſloors
of diſcontented Jebuſites) are turned into <hi>Trojan</hi> horſes, from
whence <hi>publick</hi> miſchiefs proceed! How many ſouls are
<hi>heedleſly</hi> led by theſe ſtubborn and furious guides, into a
bitter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſte of their <hi>common Mother</hi> the <hi>Church!</hi> how
many into a <hi>Peeviſh</hi> diſeſteem of their <hi>able</hi> and
<hi>pious</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructers! yea, which is moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, into a true
<hi>loathing</hi> of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Food. But to return to <hi>inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
offences,</hi> caſt your eyes I, beſeech you, about you, and every corner
will afford you ſuch, as under a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Purity,</hi> root up the
Vineyard <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99495:40"/> of <hi>God, affront Majeſty, ſcorn Laws,</hi>
and purſue their <hi>hateful deſigns,</hi> with all the violence of
<hi>diſloyal</hi> and <hi>affrighting</hi> inſinuations: whoſe deadly
Talons (like the ſoaring Eagle) are onely bowed in (I fear) for want of an
<hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> to prey and ravin. Another way of diſcerning the humour
and malice of <hi>injurious Sectaries,</hi> is in the bitter
<hi>Colycinthos</hi> they ſhred into the pots of thoſe profits they
reliſh not. Let ſome <hi>Reverend Divine</hi> but croſs and
diſcountenance <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; let him but walk in the
waies of <hi>Meek obedience</hi> and <hi>Humble</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, he ſhall be
<hi>defam'd</hi> in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, and called either a Tory, a Papiſt,
or at beſt a Papiſt in Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade; he ſhall be <hi>defrauded</hi> in
their Contracts, excluded their Houſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived utterly of all their
<hi>Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> his heart ſhall be <hi>broken</hi> with dayly
<hi>affronts</hi> and oppoſitions; his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents <hi>croſs'd,</hi> and his
deſires hinder'd: the <hi>Reverence</hi> due to his <hi>Function</hi> ſhall
be detain'd; and by telling the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar he is a man of Arbitrary Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
he preacheth Obedience to Laws, he is therefore of a perſecuting ſpirit.
And by theſe arts having prejudiced <pb n="72" facs="tcp:99495:41"/> the Factious many,
nothing but the <hi>ſalt</hi> ſcorn of a <hi>ſour face</hi> ſhall be
caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. His domeſtick <hi>neceſſities,</hi> and painful
maladies, ſhall be ſo far from any ſhare in their <hi>aid,</hi> or
<hi>pity,</hi> that they ſhall rather become matter of <hi>mirth</hi> and
<hi>mockage</hi> amongſt them; his <hi>grave</hi> ſhall be made for him,
and his <hi>knell</hi> rung in the votes of unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful people, e're
<hi>God</hi> takes him away: Nay, which is worſt of all, his <hi>holy
Labours</hi> ſhall be deſpiſed, his <hi>Rebukes</hi> ſlighted, and his
<hi>Doctrine</hi> tax'd; his <hi>Church</hi> either quite <hi>forſaken,</hi>
or thinly reſorted to. And are not theſe <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> enough to
ſtumble one; Nay, to hinder the courſe of Chriſts Goſpel? to keep many
<hi>good wits</hi> from entring upon a <hi>Function,</hi> that, in the
<hi>conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> diſcharge of it, brings nothing but
<hi>barrenneſs</hi> and <hi>vexation?</hi> Truly, if they can ſhew us no
better fruit of their <hi>boaſted</hi> holineſs, like the barren ground the
<hi>Hebrews</hi> are told of, they have a curſe at their elbow. <hi>Vae
injurianti, Wo be to that man, by whoſe injurious dealing the Offence
comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But injurious offences cannot be thought all that our Saviour
meant; <pb n="73" facs="tcp:99495:41"/> for when he puts thoſe caſes of an
<hi>offending Eye,</hi> and <hi>Hand,</hi> and <hi>Foot,</hi> we underſtand
it not of our own members, as if they ſhould offer us violence. We proceed
therefore to the laſt block, the <hi>exemplary offence;</hi> and this I will
devide into three parts, and in them ſhew you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Offence</hi> may be given by the
<hi>indiſcreet</hi> management of a good work.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the <hi>unreaſonable uſe</hi> of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different
thing: And</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the <hi>foul example</hi> of a work in its own nature
evil.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the performance of a <hi>good work</hi> commanded by
God, we are not to <hi>balk an offence,</hi> but as much as in us lies to
remove a <hi>miſpriſion.</hi> 'Tis better an offence ſhould be given,
than any of Gods ſacred Truths ſhould be betray'd. <hi>Si aliqui ſunt
infirmi, &amp; ſcentia deſtituuntur, non o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet ut nos eorum cauſa
Chriſtiana libertate fraudemur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Martyr</note>
what though ſome are weak, and deſtitute of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, there is no
reaſon that <hi>we</hi> for <hi>their</hi> cauſe ſhould be cheated of our
<hi>Chriſtian liberty. We muſt not regard their offence, who refuſe to be
healed, <pb n="74" facs="tcp:99495:42"/> unleſs we our ſelves become ſick.</hi> In
thoſe works which fall not under a <hi>ſtrict command,</hi> we are to
<hi>do</hi> that which we cannot <hi>omit</hi> without an <hi>offence;</hi> and
though 'tis certain <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nothing can
be ſo ſpoken or done, but it may be ſpoken againſt: yet when we
conſider that the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> of our Church (about which
Diſſenters make their pretence to quarrel) are but <hi>few</hi> in
<hi>number,</hi> are <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant</hi> in their <hi>nature,</hi> and
<hi>advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous</hi> to the grand deſigns of Religio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in their <hi>uſe,</hi> our Chriſtian liberty
conſiſts in this, <hi>That we have leave
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do them, without the imputation
of Sin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> nay, 'tis ſo far from
being a <hi>Sin</hi> or <hi>Offence,</hi> to comply with our neighbor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in ſuch plainly innocent uſages,
and <hi>harmleſs</hi> cuſtomes; or with the <hi>wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of our <hi>Governours,</hi> when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand us
ſuch things, that it would be both <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſcandal</hi> to
refuſe ſo to do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for our
refuſing to <hi>comply</hi> with eithe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of theſe, can hardly proceed from any better principle, than a
<hi>proud af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectation of Singularity,</hi> or at beſt from <hi>a
ſuperſtitious Scrupuloſity.</hi> St. <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> would have us abſtain from <hi>every ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
of evil;</hi> but wills us not to <pb n="75" facs="tcp:99495:42"/> 
               <hi>think</hi> every
thing evil which <hi>ſome men</hi> call ſo; for in that <hi>good old
way</hi> which the covenanting Conſiſtorians &amp; blind Papiſts call
<hi>Superſtition</hi> &amp; <hi>Hereſie,</hi> we may <hi>truly</hi>
worſhip the God of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: <hi>for God judgeth not as man
judgeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In the uſe of <hi>indifferent things,</hi> we have two
lights to ſhew us our way; <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> Faith
pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the <hi>nature</hi> of the thing it ſelf, to ſettle the
<hi>wavering</hi> conſcience: Charity preſcribing the <hi>time</hi> and
<hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> leſt we incur <hi>danger,</hi> and our weak brother
<hi>offence.</hi> Truly a ſcandal taken from the uſe of <hi>indifferent
things,</hi> if it proceed <hi>meerly</hi> of weakneſs and ignorance, is to
be <hi>pitied</hi> and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, ſerious
warnings, <hi>that we lay not a ſtumbling-block before our weak bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
that we cauſe him not to periſh for whom Chriſt dyed:</hi> and for his
own part avers, he would <hi>eat no fleſh</hi> as long as he lived, rather
than <hi>it ſhould ſtick in another mans ſtomach.</hi> But doth he mean
that his <hi>weak brother</hi> ſhould keep him <hi>for ever</hi> thus
cautelous? Or doth he yield to their <hi>infirmity</hi> onely <hi>ſo</hi>
long till the <hi>truth</hi> be taught him? Yea verily: for if our <hi>weak
brother</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="76" facs="tcp:99495:43"/> a clear inſtruction <hi>will</hi>
yet remain <hi>blind,</hi> and <hi>ſtumble</hi> at every thing, his
<hi>weakneſs</hi> is no longer to be <hi>yielded</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but to be
<hi>corrected. Pertinacia potius quam imbecillitas,</hi> ſaith a learned
Divine; you are <hi>miſtaken,</hi> my <hi>ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> brethren, you
are miſtaken, <hi>'tis rather Obſtinacy, than Infirmity; 'tis rather
wilfulneſs, than weakneſs in you,</hi> ſince there is nothing in our
<hi>worſhip</hi> of God committed that is <hi>unlawful,</hi> or
<hi>omitted</hi> that <hi>is neceſſary.</hi> You that are
<hi>Diſſenters</hi> contend for <hi>trifles,</hi> we for <hi>order</hi> and
<hi>obedience:</hi> as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, in our <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> many
people ſtumble at our <hi>publick Rites</hi> decent <hi>Geſtures,</hi> and
<hi>Vestments;</hi> and challenge us fiercely of theſe as offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But give
me leave to tell you that theſe <hi>ungrounded</hi> notions, how plauſible
ſoever, are but the <hi>dreams</hi> of ſome miſty <hi>ſleepy</hi>
brains: for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that he may keep the world un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe
<hi>deluſions,</hi> 'tis his uſual knack to <hi>burthen</hi> the forms of
Gods Worſhip with <hi>clamour</hi> and <hi>vulgar</hi> prejudice, leſt the
<hi>union</hi> of Chriſtians ſhould <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy</hi> his Kingdom, or
leſſen his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. I appeal to any <hi>indifferent man,</hi> whether it
be not more <hi>injurious</hi> 
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:99495:43"/> to Chriſtian liberty, to
follow the <hi>humorous diſlikes</hi> of <hi>private</hi> and
<hi>petu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant</hi> ſpirits, which require the omiſſion, or to yield
<hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> which by mature advice
<hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> the uſe of <hi>ſuch things,</hi> as are otherwiſe, and
in themſelves, <hi>equally indifferent</hi> for uſe or forbearance. The
reſpect of <hi>private ſcandal</hi> ceaſeth, when <hi>just authority</hi>
determines our liberty: and that <hi>restraint</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from
<hi>ſpecial</hi> duty, is of <hi>ſuperiour reaſon</hi> to that which is
deriv'd from <hi>common charity:</hi> We ought to bear a greater regard to our
<hi>publick Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> than to our <hi>private</hi> brethren; and be
more careful to <hi>obey</hi> them, than <hi>ſatisfie</hi> theſe. 'Tis
true, we are commanded <hi>be not conformed unto this world;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.2.</note> but the main import of the words, and deſign
of the Apoſtle, is in what follows: <hi>But be ye transformed by the renewing
of the mind:</hi> Newneſs of mind, is that <hi>Substantial</hi> duty of
Chriſtianity, which makes all other things <hi>lawful</hi> unto us. To the
<hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> things of the world we may <hi>conform</hi> for
<hi>quietneſs</hi> ſake; to the things of <hi>decency</hi> and
<hi>order,</hi> we ſhould conform for <hi>conſcience</hi> ſake; onely to 
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99495:44"/> the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of it we ſhould not faſhion
our ſelves.</p>
            <p>But ſince I know that our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries out of intereſt
cannot be quiet, but will (notwithſtanding all that can be ſaid to the
contrary) load <hi>innocent</hi> Ceremonies with <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Epithets
<hi>(for by this craft they get their livings)</hi> let me demand of them, How
came you ſo <hi>weak,</hi> that are ſo <hi>pure?</hi> How long hath the
<hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of theſe things been <hi>cleer'd</hi> among you? what
pains hath been taken by our <hi>reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates?</hi> What evincing
arguments have fallen from the Lips and Pens
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our reverend Divines? what
ſtone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>offence</hi> have
we not removed, to make your way cleer? And now let th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>world</hi> judge, if our <hi>holy Mother</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church, who but maintains her
<hi>ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Right</hi> and Liberty, be
to be taxed for <hi>giving offence,</hi> or not rather her <hi>wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sons,</hi> which <hi>ſhut</hi> their
<hi>eyes</hi> againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> light,
to be <hi>ſharply reproved</hi> for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>wilful</hi> diſobedience. Yet am I no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſo uncharitable to think, that every
one which diſſents from the doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of this or that Church muſt be ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized for a
Schiſmatick: No, if a diſſenter be <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>modeſt,
humble</hi> 
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:99495:44"/> and <hi>holy,</hi> and makes no
<hi>breach</hi> in the Church's <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> ſuch a one hath the temper
of a <hi>ſober</hi> Chriſtian, and will do no <hi>miſchief</hi> to
Religion: but when diſſenting about <hi>indifferent</hi> things, is managed
with <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Paſſion, Rage</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> tending
to the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> of Government and <hi>good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> Then
'tis manifeſt there is ſomething more in the caſe than
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and the man is become <hi>Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> When a weak
ſcruple againſt <hi>the Sign of the Croſs,</hi> ſhall make men
<hi>Rebels</hi> againſt the <hi>Crown;</hi> when a
<hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious</hi> abhorrence of a <hi>white Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,</hi> ſhall
make us dye our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>blood;</hi> and a <hi>furious</hi> zeal
againſt an <hi>Organ,</hi> ſhall make men call for the confuſed noiſe
of <hi>Drums</hi> and <hi>Trumpets,</hi> 'tis manifeſt they have loſt the
temper of <hi>ſober Chriſtians,</hi> and deſerve the hateful name of
<hi>Rebels,</hi> as well as Schiſmaticks. 'Tis a <hi>ſtrange
deluſion</hi> that hath ſeized ſome which ſcruple at an innocent
Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who againſt all <hi>convictions</hi> and armies of reaſon will
be <hi>troubled,</hi> and will not underſtand; this is very bad; <hi>but 'tis
worſe that he ſhould think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the more godly man, for being 
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99495:45"/> thus troubled and diſeas'd;</hi> and that upon this
account he ſhall fall out with his lawful Soveraign, calumniate his Actions,
reproach his Counſellors, abuſe his ſubjects, and quarrel with his
Government, and deſpiſe it; this man <hi>nurſes</hi> his ſcruple, and
inſtead of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a <hi>Boyl,</hi> dies of a <hi>Cancer:</hi> or is like a
man that hath ſtrained his foot, and keeps his
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe; but by lying <hi>long</hi>
there, falls into a <hi>Lip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thymie,</hi> and that bears him to his grave. Thus calling
themſelves to <hi>doubtful diſputations,</hi> (inſtead of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing
known duties), they go on deceiving and being deceived, to their own
diſcomfort here, and miſery hereafter. But I gladly ſhift the Scene;
intreating my diſſenting and ſcrupulous brethren to remember, it is all
our duties to obey and do what is <hi>commanded;</hi> not <hi>judging</hi> our
Judges, but quietly ſubmitting to their <hi>Injunctions, who watch for our
ſouls, and must give an account to God.</hi> But if ſo many miſchiefs and
<hi>offences</hi> proceed from <hi>indifferent things,</hi> what ſhall we
think of <hi>groſs</hi> and <hi>infectious</hi> evils, the
<hi>miſleading</hi> acts of the vitious or indulgent Ruler, the
<hi>Riots</hi> and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines</hi> 
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:99495:45"/> of the rich, the
<hi>leud</hi> examples of <hi>Church-men, Parents</hi> and <hi>Maſters,
do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick fails,</hi> the <hi>foul</hi> ſlips of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious,</hi>
the <hi>mutual</hi> ſeducements of men and women by ſcandalous ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits,
<hi>Cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Ruler is firſt. As <hi>Jacobs</hi> Sheep brought forth Lambs
agreeing in colour with the pill'd rods they caſt their eyes on; ſo many
people, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of a <hi>greedy hope</hi> to thrive by a <hi>ſervile</hi>
imitation, or out of a <hi>vain</hi> ambition to follow their betters, take
courſes of the ſame tincture with the <hi>Scepters</hi> of Authority. When
the Clock ſtrikes not in due ſeaſon, we blame not the weights or
movement, but the Clock-keeper; and whom are the fails of the Vulgar aſcribed
to, but their eminent Guides? Let <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tazar</hi> carouze in the
<hi>hallowed boles</hi> of the Temple, and all the Court will pledge him: let
Queen <hi>Vaſti</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul her husband, and all the ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dames in
the Country-provinces will take the Reins into their own hands. <hi>Why did the
Heathens ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly rage? who did the people ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a vain thing?</hi>
The <hi>Pſalmographer</hi> reſolves us, <hi>The Rulers of the earth 
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99495:46"/> took counſel together againſt the Lord, and againſt
his Anointed.</hi> Who could imagine a people ſo laden with the favours of a
gracious <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that ſaw their <hi>ſick</hi> reſtored,
their <hi>blind</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, their <hi>lame</hi> walking, and their
<hi>dumb</hi> ſpeaking; yea, their <hi>dead</hi> bodies brought to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ife! Who would imagine after
theſe <hi>beneficial</hi> works, they ſhould put him to ſo baſe and
bitter a death? Had not <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilat,</hi> had not
<hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> had not the Chief Prieſts and the
<hi>Ruling Elders</hi> took counſel together againſt the <hi>Lord, and
againſt his Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</hi> Therefore, as if the <hi>guilt</hi> of all this
had ſtuck on the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> the holy Pſalmiſt
directs his advice to them onely: Be wiſe now therefore, <hi>O ye Kings, be
learned ye that are Judges of the Earth.</hi> It is with men as with fiſhes,
if the head begins to putriſy, the body can be worth nothing; if the head be
<hi>ſick</hi> what can the heart do but <hi>faint,</hi> and the body but
<hi>languiſh? If a Ruler hearken to lyes,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>)
<hi>all his ſervants are wicked.</hi> And here turning our woe on the
<hi>Romiſh</hi> and <hi>Factious Grandees</hi> that have hearkned to lyes, 
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99495:46"/> and led people into <hi>miſchievous</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions:
how are we bound to bleſs God for the <hi>upright</hi> and moderate ſway,
the inoffenſive and meek car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of our Royal Head, and his
<hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bordinate</hi> Deputies, whoſe very <hi>lives</hi> may as well
ſilence a ſaucy <hi>Libeller,</hi> as their authority?</p>
            <p>But this word gives them another memento: <hi>Authority</hi> hath
a <hi>Sword</hi> in her hand; and if ſhe <hi>bear it in vain,</hi> ſin is
heartned, and <hi>offences given.</hi> The old Gyants were called
<hi>Nephilim,</hi> Cadentes, not as if they fell from Heaven, but becauſe
other men aſrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their grim looks, were ready to fall down and
ſwoon away. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, 'tis rather the over-<hi>gentle,</hi> than the
<hi>terrible</hi> Rulers, are the right <hi>Nephilim,</hi> that make men fall
into a cuſtome of ſinning: for as <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod caſt on the ground
became a <hi>Serpent,</hi> ſo the Rod of <hi>Juſtice</hi> that falls from
the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> hands for earthly reſpects, what does it prove but
a deſtroying, a poyſoning Serpent? therefore is it good Counſel given by
the Son of <hi>Syrac, Let no man ſeek to be a Judge, who is not able to take
away iniquity, leſt at any time he fear the perſon of <pb n="84" facs="tcp:99495:47"/>
the mighty, and lay a ſtumbling-block in the way of uprightneſs.</hi>
Honour on a Fools back is as Snow in Summer, as Rain in the time of Harveſt,
not onely unfit for himſelf; but <hi>pernitious</hi> to others: for as
Summer-Snows cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Fruits, and Harveſt-Showers rot the Corn; ſo a
weak Ruler is the ſpoil of a Country. And though we may thank God that even
this way we are better provided, yet our Saviours Item (like <hi>Philip</hi>'s
boy) may ſtand for a Remembrance; when <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>partiality</hi>
would get admiſſion, <hi>Voe Rectoribus,</hi> wo be to the <hi>exalted</hi>
man by whom the <hi>offence</hi> comes.</p>
            <p>And now if oyled Paper would be writ on, I could try the Rich of
this world how prone they are to ſcatter Offences; as St. <hi>Paul</hi>
ſays, <hi>They fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> themſelves
into divers ſnares and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations,</hi> and bring others into the ſame
trap. Riches in the Hebrew Dialect have a name that implies <hi>Stability;</hi>
they are called <hi>Jechum,</hi> as if they made a man to ſtand ſure: but
if they make our <hi>ſelves</hi> ſtand, and <hi>others</hi> fall, what are
they but <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon?</hi> Our Saviours <pb n="85" facs="tcp:99495:47"/> Churl
was arrayed in Purple, which is a bloudy colour; and how many of our great mens
Robes are dyed in the <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>wrack,</hi> and offenſive
ſpoil of their poor Neighbours; yea, in the <hi>pillage</hi> of the
<hi>Temples?</hi> How many of theſe <hi>dry Nurſes</hi> have Breaſts
great enough, but yield no Milk for the <hi>Babes of Chriſt,</hi> whoſe
houſes ſtand like Beech-trees, onely for <hi>Beaſts</hi> and
<hi>Drunkards</hi> to be ſheltered under; or like <hi>Oaks of Baſhan</hi>
(as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaks) that have nothing but A corns for a few Swine, while
the poor and indigent are deni'd ſitting relief, and forced to rob, pilfer,
and <hi>offend</hi> God, if not to challenge him of unjuſt partiality?</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis another offence I take it in men of Quality, that
many of them are become the <hi>Patrons</hi> of Schiſm, and inſtead of
their true Miſtriſs, that <hi>heavenly</hi> and <hi>religious</hi>
Wiſdom, that is both <hi>pure and peaceable,</hi> like Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Knights in the
Pores legend, have embraced an ugly Witch with her angry and fantaſtical
face, the <hi>masked</hi> Hypocriſie of cunning <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots;</hi> that
ſuch men whom our <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits</hi> have ſpewed out for retaining 
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99495:48"/> their <hi>old Principles</hi> of <hi>Diſobedience,
Tumult, Schiſm,</hi> or <hi>Hereſie,</hi> ſhall by theſe <hi>great</hi>
ones be <hi>hug'd</hi> and liſtened to as the onely <hi>Oracles</hi> of
Infallibility. O how they <hi>bleſs</hi> and <hi>admire</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
(and are proclaimed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) as the grand <hi>Sticklers</hi> of their
<hi>Party,</hi> becauſe they have a <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Levite to their
Prieſt!</hi> Is not this an <hi>offence,</hi> that you that impoſe
<hi>Laws</hi> upon us, are the <hi>first</hi> breakers of them your ſelves,
and think you <hi>do God good ſervice,</hi> while you fight againſt him,
<hi>in diſturbing the peace of the Church and Kingdom?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ubi ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mior prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogativa, ibi major culpa.
<hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian,</hi> lib. 4. de guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. Dei.</note> Combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible matter is
not more incident to ruine by its vicinity to the flames, than your
<hi>inferiours</hi> are by tracing your ſteps. You know well, the
<hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> that belongs to your
<hi>qualities,</hi> cannot exempt you from the common Obligation and <hi>Law of
Religion;</hi> but the greater your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are, the more <hi>enforcing</hi>
is your <hi>intereſt</hi> to be religious, becauſe your Examples are more
leading and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ential. Be not, I beſeech you, the Ring-leaders into
<hi>Schiſm,</hi> but be Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of ſolid Piety and ſincere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:
for this will <hi>adorn your bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,</hi> 
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:99495:48"/> and ennoble
your <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Names</hi> in the laſting Records of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. And
on the contrary, wo be to them that adde fuel to the fire of Diſſention:
<hi>Voe diviti, Wo be to the man by whoſe abuſed riches or honours the
offence comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis a great exemplary <hi>offence</hi> in the judgment
of all the <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced</hi> world, that our
<hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> Brethren give, in ſeparating from the <hi>Church</hi>
of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe in our publick Service we uſe Set Forms of
Prayer: and becauſe they think themſelves innocent, though but for the
advantage of accuſing us firſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s laying theſe <hi>ſtumbling-blocks</hi> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way to <hi>Peace</hi> and
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> I ſhall tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> off
this <hi>Sanctimonious Vizor,</hi> (mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> onely to ſtartle the <hi>unwary admirers,</hi> that gaze on the
outſide onely) and make it appear to all that are not guarded with the Shield
and Buckle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Irrationality,
That they themſelves are the men by whom the offence comes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that I may leave them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out quarrel, I ſhall make them
both Judge and Party, and endeavour to convict or acquit them by a Jury of 
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99495:49"/> their own packing, and their own Creatures being Judges.
This makes Religion <hi>contemptible</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xter</hi>)
<hi>when we are perceived to place Religion in unwarrantable Separations, and
affected Singularities from a true Church, and have no other pretence, but that
they pray by a Book, and we pray without one:</hi> Theſe are the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints
that make our Houſes and Streets ring, that our <hi>Governours</hi> are
Perſecutors, becauſe they would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel you to hear a man that is
<hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable,</hi> and <hi>pray</hi> with ſuch as uſe the
<hi>Liturgie,</hi> and <hi>communicate with a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Congregation.</hi>
Theſe are the <hi>no Crimes</hi> you charge on the <hi>Churches</hi> ſcore,
and the <hi>foundation</hi> on which you build the Wall of <hi>Separation,</hi>
and eſtrange your ſelves from <hi>the beſt Church in the world.</hi> But
how you will anſwer this to God Almighty in the Great and Terrible Day, is my
wonder and aſtoniſhment: And therefore entreat you to conſider whether
theſe are <hi>ſufficient</hi> cauſes to make <hi>Rents</hi> and
<hi>Diviſions</hi> in the Church, and raiſe Contentions and
<hi>Heart-burnings</hi> amongſt thoſe which agree in all
<hi>fundamental</hi> truths. No, <pb n="89" facs="tcp:99495:49"/> but rather on the
contrary, if you had (as <hi>God bethanked</hi> you have not) a <hi>just</hi>
cauſe to refuſe <hi>Communion</hi> with our Church in ſome inſtances;
yet you ought not therefore to proceed to a <hi>total Separation</hi> from it,
or to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect <hi>new Churches</hi> in contradiſtinction to us, or gratifie
the <hi>humorous</hi> diſlikes of them that do, by joyning with them. You
often call us Popiſh Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latical Prieſts; but if you will believe Mr.
<hi>Baxter,</hi> he ſays. <hi>You are the great Factors of</hi> Rome, <hi>and
<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pholders of the Triple Crown: For</hi> (ſaith he)<note place="margin">Defence of the <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Love</hi> p. 52.</note>
               <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have been drawn to</hi> Popery, <hi>or</hi> confirmed <hi>in
it by</hi> your Separation <hi>already; and I am perſwaded that all the
Arguments elſe in</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>and all other Books, have not done
ſo</hi> much <hi>to make</hi> Papiſts <hi>in</hi> England, <hi>as the</hi>
Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among our ſelves; <hi>yea, ſome Profeſſors of</hi>
ſtrictneſs <hi>in Religion, and of great eſteem for</hi> godlineſs,
<hi>have tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> Papiſts <hi>themſelves, when they were</hi> giddied
<hi>and</hi> wearied <hi>with turning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They know but little of the world, who perceive not that our
Differences are the Contrivances of the <hi>Romiſh Cabal</hi> to ruine us:
Read the Biſhop of <hi>Rhodes</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Henry</hi> the 
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:99495:50"/> Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Campanella</hi>'s
Spaniſh Monarchy; where, after a long diſcourſe of the intended
Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>England</hi> by the Monarchs of <hi>Spain</hi> and
<hi>France</hi> (incited thereto by the Commands and Benedictions of
<hi>Rome,</hi> as well as their own <hi>Ambition</hi>) they eſpecially
declare their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the means and inſtruments to be employ'd for the
<hi>Ruine</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church in this ſort, that there was
no better Artifice, than <hi>by cauſing Diviſions and Diſſentions among
the Engliſh:</hi> And to this purpoſe they adviſed it as the onely way,
to erect certain <hi>Schools</hi> and <hi>Academies</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi>
that the Students thereof may diſſeminate Seeds of <hi>Diviſion</hi> in
<hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Theological</hi> Sciences: which would
<hi>diſcompoſe</hi> their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <hi>unſettle</hi> their
Judgments: for (ſay they) the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to
<hi>Novelties,</hi> and are no leſs violent in <hi>defending</hi> them. And
how <hi>conſiderable</hi> the effects of this Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance has been, their
late <hi>horrid</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt our gracious <hi>King,</hi> do
manifeſt. And you, my diſſenting Brethren, of whom it may be ſaid, as
<hi>Chemnitius</hi> ſpake of the Monks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <pb n="91" facs="tcp:99495:50"/>
               <hi>Pelagianiſm,</hi> You defie the Heretick, and foſter the Hereſie: for
while you ſeparate from us, you do no leſs than make your ſelves Agents
to accompliſh their deſignes, in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing a Church <hi>you acknowledge
to be true,</hi> and promote the Errours of Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Many ſad Examples might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to this purpoſe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Dr. <hi>Aſhton</hi>'s Poſtſcript to the caſe
of Scandal</note> but I delight not to vex a <hi>Wound</hi> by a continued
application of <hi>Corroſives:</hi> I ſhall therefore proceed to anſwer
the main Objections againſt the uſe of our <hi>Common-prayer</hi>-book; the
firſt of which is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Praying by a Set Form, is a humane invention, and
ſinful, becauſe not commanded in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwering whereof, I muſt invoke again the
aſſiſtance of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> (for they that raiſe theſe
Spectrums are beſt skill'd in laying them:) 
<q rend="inline">
                  <note place="margin">Lib. id. pag. 53. ad
60.</note>"If by falſe Worſhip, ſaith he, you mean <hi>forbidden</hi> or
not <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,</hi> we (i. e. the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>) <hi>worſhip
God falſly every day, and in ſome part of the matter, very oft</hi> our
<hi>Diſorders, Confuſions, Tautologies,</hi> and <hi>unfit</hi>
Expreſſions are all <hi>forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> 
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:99495:51"/> and ſo
falſe Worſhip: and if God <hi>prohibit</hi> it in the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> he
<hi>prohibits</hi> the ſame in <hi>extemporate Prayers;</hi> in which ſome
good Chriſtians are as <hi>failing</hi> as the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy. And as the words of
the <hi>Liturgie</hi> are not commanded in <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſo neither are
the words of our <hi>extemporate</hi> or <hi>ſtudied</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons or
<hi>Prayers.</hi> God hateth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>ſin</hi> in every <hi>Prayer,</hi>
but he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>the avoiding of Prayer and due Communion much more;</hi> and
you but ſtrain at <hi>Gnats</hi> and ſwallow <hi>Camels,</hi> while you
thus eagerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the Shadow, and let the Subſtance glide from you;
giving us cauſe to think theſe <hi>Niceties</hi> are but <hi>the Bones that
the Devil throws amongst us to break our Teeth with, and in the mean ſpace
reject the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Food of our Souls.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Open your Eyes, I beſeech you, and you will eaſily diſcern
how you are <hi>impoſed</hi> on, and made the <hi>Engines</hi> of their
<hi>Malice,</hi> who would deſtroy both <hi>us</hi> and <hi>you.</hi>
Methinks I hear the <hi>Papiſts, Independents, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and
<hi>Quakers,</hi> hiſſing each Party on, ſaying, <hi>There, there, ſo
would we have <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99495:51"/> it:</hi> One while crying, Throw
<hi>Dirt</hi> enough on the <hi>Surplice,</hi> and be ſure ſome will
<hi>ſtick;</hi> call the <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>Croſs</hi> the Mark of
the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> tear in pieces their <hi>Liturgie,</hi> and call it
<hi>the Popiſh Maſs-book:</hi> Another Sect ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Bate them
nothing;</hi> and others, <hi>Stand it out, and yield to nothing;</hi> with a
deal more of this inſignificant <hi>Jargon:</hi> Who are well aſſured,
that if there be once a right Underſtanding, and conſequently a mutual
Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> and <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi>
Parties, they muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dwindle into their <hi>Original</hi>
No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; or like rotten Houſes, when the ſubſtantial <hi>Props</hi> they
lean on are taken away, moulter to dirt, and bury themſelves in their own
Ruines. Have a care therefore you warm not theſe <hi>Vipers</hi> any longer
in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, by eſpouſing their <hi>Quarrels:</hi> for if ever they
come to be ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with <hi>power,</hi> will turn their ſtings
againſt their Nouriſhers; as the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents</hi> have done againſt
you once already.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But the <hi>Covenant</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the
Scotch Covenant) (ſay they) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have lifted up our hands to the 
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:99495:52"/> moſt High, makes it unlawful to hold Communion with any
that uſe a Liturgy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall again make bold with Mr.
<hi>Baxter</hi> for this reaſon, that Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers affirm, there needs no greater
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of an <hi>Offender,</hi> than the <hi>Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of one
of the <hi>Complices:</hi> His words in anſwer to this Objection are theſe:

<q rend="inline">"No man of us all hath need or ought to go to the
Covenant to know what is his duty in the <hi>Worſhip of God,</hi> but onely
to the <hi>Scriptures:</hi> for if <hi>Scripture</hi> make it not a duty, the
<hi>Magiſtrates Law</hi> will make it a <hi>ſin;</hi> and if
<hi>Scripture</hi> make it <hi>not a ſin,</hi> the Magiſtrates
<hi>Command</hi> will make it a <hi>duty.</hi>"</q> And in <hi>p.</hi> 9. and
<hi>p.</hi> 88. of his <hi>Defence of the Principles of Love,</hi> reſolves
it thus: 
<q rend="inline">"To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <hi>no</hi> publick Worſhip, or a
<hi>worſe,</hi> before the <hi>Liturgie,</hi> is <hi>deformation</hi> and
prophaneneſs: <hi>for all the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches in Chriſtendom do
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to hold Communion with the Church of</hi> England <hi>in their
Liturgie,</hi> if they come amongſt us where 'tis uſed: Therefore it
ſeems to me to be <hi>Perjury</hi> and <hi>Covenant-breaking,</hi> either to
prefer <hi>no</hi> publick Worſhip <pb n="95" facs="tcp:99495:52"/> before the
<hi>Liturgie,</hi> or <hi>to refuſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Churches that uſe
it, as a thing meerly on that account un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider further, that your Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſavours of Novelty,
(which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Wiſe and Holy, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further aggravation, renders it
ſcandalous) and our practice cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſponds with Antiquity, whoſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom
in the firſt and pureſt times was, to pray by Forms: Nay, the
<hi>Antients</hi> pronounc'd it a <hi>ſin</hi> to do otherwiſe in their
<hi>publick Devotions.</hi> And though I urge not their Practices and
Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, as Principles of <hi>infallible</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to <hi>command</hi>
your belief; yet I hope you will admit them as <hi>grounds of credibility,</hi>
to <hi>facilitate</hi> your aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, being handed to us by thoſe that
cannot be imagined <hi>not to know,</hi> being ſo <hi>near;</hi> nor be
ſuſpected to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine</hi> flalſly to impoſe on us, being ſo
<hi>pious.</hi> And if you want an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, take it from the Diſciples; who
out of a ſenſe of their own wants, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpake their Maſter, thus:
<hi>Teach us to pray, as John taught his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore, conſider in <hi>time,</hi> what you
are doing: for if <pb n="96" facs="tcp:99495:53"/> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> prophecies right, he
tells you, <hi>That Separating will at laſt ruine the ſeparate Churches
themſelves: for no inſtance can be given</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of a
ſeparate Church of a hundred years ſtanding.</hi> To conclude, the ſame
Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſaith, <hi>The Proteſtant Religion muſt be kept up by the means
of the Pariſh-Miniſters, and by the Doctrine and Worſhip then performed;
and they that think and endeavour that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this, of what
ſide ſoever, ſhall have the hearty thanks and concurrence of the
Papiſts.</hi> O that now, my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren, you would be
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to lay aſide all <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>partiality,
ſelf-ends</hi> and intereſts, <hi>and follow the things that make for
peace:</hi> Suffer your <hi>Reaſons</hi> to awake; put on <hi>Modeſty,</hi>
be clothed with Humility, and call no men, or decent Cuſtom, Popiſh or
Antichriſtian, till you are aſſured by an infallible ſigne it is ſo;
leſt you be found <hi>fighters againſt God, and ſlanderers of your
Brethren:</hi> Be not <hi>raſh</hi> cenſurers, but judge <hi>righteous
judgment,</hi> leſt you abuſe the truth it ſelf, <hi>and call the
Spouſe of Chriſt an Harlot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> is bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd, <pb n="97" facs="tcp:99495:53"/>
hath no <hi>Idols</hi> to obſcure, no ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Cheat</hi> with which
to delude you; for the repreſenting of which, we ſhould ſtand either in
need of <hi>darkneſs,</hi> or a <hi>falſe light:</hi> we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in
our <hi>publick profeſſion</hi> which the <hi>wiſest</hi> men, the
<hi>moſt pious</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, may not <hi>practice;</hi> nothing in our
<hi>Faith</hi> which they ought not <hi>ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly</hi> to believe. It is
onely want of Enquiry, and a ſober Examination, that the <hi>purity</hi> of
our Churches <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> is not more generally <hi>embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced;</hi> 'tis
becauſe the calmneſs and <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety</hi> of its <hi>Devotion,</hi> the
moderation of its <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> the largeneſs of its
<hi>Charity,</hi> are not more impartially en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into, that men miſtake
us, <hi>divide</hi> from our <hi>Communion,</hi> trouble the world with their
<hi>impertinent</hi> noiſe and clamour, and adminiſter matter of
<hi>offence</hi> to many thouſands in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who are hardened
into an utter neglect of Godlineſs by the unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable
<hi>Singularities,</hi> and the ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſins, eſpecially of thoſe
Profeſſors that have been moſt addicted to <hi>ſinful Separations;</hi>
without receiving <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> or giving a reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, I am afraid that <pb n="98" facs="tcp:99495:54"/> all thoſe
<hi>Scruples</hi> that have been ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to vindicate a <hi>Separation</hi> from
our <hi>Communion,</hi> will be found too light at <hi>the day of the
Lord,</hi> to counterpoiſe the vaſt guilt of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and
<hi>Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> Could you make it appear that your Salvation was in
the leaſt <hi>hazarded</hi> by Communion with us; if you could not have
<hi>Peace,</hi> but upon thoſe ill terms of parting with <hi>Truth</hi> and
<hi>Holineſs;</hi> could you demonſtrate that in <hi>any thing</hi> we are
departed from the <hi>true Church,</hi> your Separation was warrantable: but
ſince 'tis evident our Church hath preſerved intire <hi>that Faith which
was once delivered to the Saints,</hi> without any <hi>loſs</hi> or
<hi>innovation;</hi> ſince all the Laws and Rules of <hi>holy</hi> and
Chriſtian life, are by our Church <hi>taught;</hi> ſince men may
<hi>conform</hi> to all the Conſtitutions of our <hi>Church,</hi> and yet be
as <hi>holy</hi> as the <hi>best</hi> of Saints in any Age of the world;
ſince there is nothing herein <hi>commanded,</hi> that ever God did forbid;
and ſince all this <hi>we are able to prove</hi> by the cleareſt
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations, it muſt neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, they incur a Wo that call
good evil, and light darkneſs.</p>
            <p n="4">4. 'Tis no leſs a hainous <hi>offence</hi> alſo 
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:99495:54"/> to ſeparate from a true Church, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence that
notoriouſly <hi>ſinful Members</hi> are received into <hi>Communion</hi>
with it. This is to ſtrain at a <hi>Gnat,</hi> and ſwallow a
<hi>Spider;</hi> and to prevent an <hi>imaginary</hi> guilt of Pollution by
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, incur a real guilt of <hi>Schiſm</hi> in themſelves. And though by
diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing with <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> they magnifie
themſelves, and <hi>brand</hi> thoſe they ſeparate from, with the
diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Epithets of <hi>ungodly</hi> and <hi>profane,</hi> and with the
<hi>Whore</hi> in the Proverbs, <hi>wipe their mouths,</hi> and ſay, <hi>they
have done no harm;</hi> yet in the judgment of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the ſin of
Separation is ſo dangerouſly infectious, that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons guilty of it
are to be ſet in the <hi>first</hi> rate of Offenders, and to be
<hi>ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> as ſoon as deſcried: <hi>Mark them that cauſe
Diviſions and Offences, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine you have learned, and avoid
them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſt attentè, diligenter,
quaſi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes è ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetis. <hi>Biza</hi> in
loc.</note> Diviſions are the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences</hi> that put the Orbs of
<hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences</hi> into <hi>motion,</hi> and are the prime
<hi>ſubverſion</hi> of the Church; which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe is rarely endamaged:
for whilſt it is <hi>united,</hi> Satan is not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, nor
<hi>Scandals</hi> ſtarted; which makes the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in another
place ſo <pb n="100" facs="tcp:99495:55"/> paſſionately reſent the injury offered
to the Church by Diviſions, that he wiſhes they were <hi>cut off</hi> that
trouble it, by unſetling and removing its Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries from their firſt
Station.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And you will have no cauſe to think this a ſevere proceſs,
ſince there is <hi>more miſchief</hi> threatned to the Church of God, and
<hi>leſs hopes of reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> in a <hi>Separatiſt,</hi> than a more
no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified <hi>Malefactor:</hi> A debauch'd man, if diſcreetly reprehended,
will <hi>bluſh</hi> and <hi>tremble</hi> at his Miſcarriage; but an
<hi>Ableptick Schiſm-Maſter</hi> will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, inſult, and ſpurn at
him, that by a modeſt Reproof would <hi>turn him from the errour of his
way;</hi> beſides, a Sect-maker diſturbs the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church,
tears its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and paves a Cauſey to <hi>deſtruction,</hi>
whilſt the other onely perverts himſelf, and diſquiets but his own
Conſcience. But admit ſome of the <hi>Members</hi> of our Church were as
bad as they would render them, it makes no <hi>Pallizado</hi> for their
<hi>Conventicle:</hi> for as long as the Church ſojourneth on Earth, bad men
will be mixed with the good; and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a <hi>ſharp
reprehenſion</hi> (in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi> in Mat. 13.36</note> 
               <hi>that tumultuouſly 
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:99495:55"/> depart from the Church, or by unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
rigidneſs endeavour to overthrow it.</hi> And Chriſt Jeſus in propounding
this Parable (ſaith the ſame Author) would <hi>bridle</hi> and
<hi>moderate</hi> their Zeal who think it <hi>unlawful</hi> to have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
with none but <hi>pure Angels;</hi> and they that prepoſterouſly make
haſte to root out all that diſpleaſeth them, do as much as in them is,
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Chriſts Judgment,</hi> and uſurp <hi>the Angels
Office.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> tells us,<note place="margin">Expoſ. on St.
<hi>Jude,</hi> v. 9. Amplified on <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.2</note> that <hi>faults in
the manners of Profeſſors, is no warrant for our Separation: for tho
vices</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>appear in the lives of Miniſters and People; ſo
long as true Religion is taught, and the Sacraments duely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, it is
a Church, and we may not depart from it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hilderſham</hi> makes it is Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Obſervation
upon the fourth of St. <hi>John</hi> 22. 
<note place="margin">Lecture the 36.</note>
               <hi>That thoſe
Aſſemblies that enjoy the Word and Doctrine of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though they may
have many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in them, are to be acknowledged the true Churches of
God, and ſuch as none of the faithful may make ſeparation from.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am almoſt aſſured, they would <pb n="102" facs="tcp:99495:56"/> think
it little leſs than <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> not to allow theſe men to be
<hi>theirs;</hi> and whether it be not an <hi>offence</hi> for thoſe of a
<hi>ſecond Edition</hi> to make their <hi>practices</hi> claſh with theſe
<hi>allowed Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> let <hi>Conſcience</hi> judge: Onely give me
leave to make this uſe of their Doctrine, <hi>That 'tis extreamly ſinful
for</hi> Presbyterians <hi>to ſeparate from the Church of</hi> England,
<hi>their own cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Teachers being Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our bleſſed Saviour refuſed not to communicate with the
Twelve, though he knew <hi>one of them was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil;</hi> nay, he lived and
died in <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> though 'twas
abominably corrupted; and was ſo <hi>indulgent</hi> and <hi>graciouſly
appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable</hi> to ſinners, that the Phariſees call'd him a Companion and
Friend of Publicans and Sinners.</p>
            <p>One reaſon why Chriſt would be baptized among the <hi>common
ſort,</hi> is rendred by <hi>Spanheim</hi> to be, that he might convince the
World he was no Friend to <hi>thoſe Opinions</hi> that debarred men from
<hi>frequenting</hi> the means of their <hi>Salvation,</hi> under the colour of
their preſent <hi>unworthineſs:</hi> for <hi>he came not to call the
righteous, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners <pb n="103" facs="tcp:99495:56"/> to repentance.</hi> It is the
works, not the workers of darkneſs, that the Apoſtle enjoyns us to have
<hi>no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with. Judas</hi> his perſonal action in eating the
<hi>Paſcal Lamb,</hi> was an <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;</hi> but it had no
<hi>reflection</hi> on the Apoſtles that <hi>communicated</hi> with him: for
as their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> did not <hi>ſanctifie</hi> him,
neither did <hi>his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> defile them, or <hi>hinder</hi> the benefit
of their <hi>worthy receiving.</hi> The Sons of <hi>Ely</hi> were
<hi>practically</hi> vitious, <hi>ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> Sons of
<hi>Belial;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.29.</note> yet the People that
communicated <hi>with them</hi> were <hi>Gods people.</hi> Scripture almoſt
every where is loud in the commendation of <hi>unanimous</hi> Congregations;
but ſtigmatizeth the <hi>privacy</hi> of a <hi>disjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it fit for you, my <hi>diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Brethren,</hi>
to complain againſt our <hi>Parochial Communions:</hi> for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation
of our Offences, is no Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge nor Plea before Gods dreadful Tribunal, for
the proſecution of your own, though ſpun with a finer thread: <hi>Firſt
cast out the beam that is in your own eye, and then you may ſee clearer to
take the mote out of your brothers eye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:99495:57"/>Give me leave, I pray you, <hi>out of love to
your Souls and the Church's peace,</hi> to be plain with you: for I muſt not,
I dare not <hi>flatter</hi> you, by ſowing <hi>Pillows</hi> under your
Elbows, and calling you <hi>pretious Souls, Gods elect people,</hi> and your
lawleſs Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings the <hi>Aſſembly of Saints,</hi> until I have other
proof of your immunity from the common Errours of others, beſides your own
naked affirmations. Do not delude your ſelves, nor ſuffer your
<hi>Hirelings</hi> to do it: you are not <hi>better</hi> than others, but are
<hi>dayly</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Covetouſneſs, Envy,
Malice,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs, Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Lying,
Over-reaching,</hi> and <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> to every <hi>diſcerning</hi>
eye; and the reaſon why it is no more <hi>notorious</hi> to the
<hi>common</hi> view, is, you have learn'd the <hi>knack</hi> to <hi>indulge
each other in your cloſe iniquities,</hi> to <hi>palliate</hi> your
<hi>open</hi> wickedneſs, and obſcure your <hi>own</hi> Crimes by
<hi>defaming others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But were you as eminent <hi>Veſſels of Honour</hi> as you
would be <hi>thought</hi> to be, yet you may not diſdain thoſe that are but
of <hi>wood</hi> and <hi>ſtone,</hi> as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy your Societies. 'Tis one of
<hi>Machiavil</hi>'s principles, that who they <pb n="105" facs="tcp:99495:57"/> ſtagger
with one wrong, they muſt utterly caſt down with more; which you make your
practice, if you endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour not by uniting with us, to ward off that blow that
from the hand of our common Enemy is falling on us. 'Twould well beſeem the
<hi>goodneſs</hi> you pretend, to <hi>return</hi> and ſtrengthen us with
your better Members (if you have any ſuch) that we may be thereby enabled to
<hi>mend</hi> what is <hi>amiſs,</hi> and bleſs God for the mercy of
<hi>making men to be of one mind in a houſe, and ſtilling the Outrage of an
unruly Faction:</hi> And I beſeech God Almighty to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due us all with a
ſorrowful apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all our Offences, <hi>that our Parochial
Aſſemblies may be more ſober and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout, and that your ſeparate
Churches may be more juſt, humble, and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; that we may all ſtudy
to preſerve the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, all minding the
ſame thing; and that there may be no Diviſions amongst us, but that with
one mind and one mouth we may ſerve the living God; that his Name may be
glorified, our Sins purged, all our Souls ſaved, and avoid that wo that
belongs to them that cauſe Diviſions and Offences. Ve Segregatori,</hi> 
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:99495:58"/> Wo be to them that ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſenſual,
having not the Spirit.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Neglecting the ſervice of God in the publick Offices of
Religion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>fallacious</hi> pretext of being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove thoſe
ſubſidiary helps, or being better employ'd on the Lords day at home, is a
moſt injurious and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous offence. <hi>Do you provoke the Lord to
jealouſie? are you wiſer than he,</hi> that you uſurp a priviledge of
doing onely <hi>what is right in your own eyes,</hi> in oppoſition to the
all-wiſe commands of a <hi>Deity?</hi> Many <hi>Opinioniſts</hi> have done
wickedly; but this in <hi>pride and ingratitude exceeds them all. Wo be to him
that is alone,</hi> in the want of a ſpiritual Guide to <hi>correct</hi> his
wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and <hi>direct</hi> his feet in the right paths. For ſo
pernicious is an <hi>affected</hi> curioſity to be wiſer than our
<hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> that it forces men upon dangerous
precipices to their deſtruction: Whereas abiding in their <hi>Station</hi>
with a meek and humble <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> in a plain and well-ordered
Devotion, would have made them better men, if not more knowing Chriſtians. To
decline <hi>offences,</hi> to be careful and conſcientious in our 
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:99495:58"/> ſeveral actions, is a purity that every man ought to
ſtrive after; but to <hi>cheat</hi> the world into a belief that we do ſo,
onely by <hi>ſeparating</hi> from our Brethren, is a <hi>double
iniquity.</hi> You think you are above Ordinances; but I doubt it is nothing
but a <hi>wanton</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, and <hi>proud</hi> temper of ſpirit, that
makes you boaſt ſo: and if your own <hi>arrogance</hi> and
<hi>preſumption</hi> would give you leave to lay aſide the <hi>flattering
glaſs</hi> of Self-love, you would find you ſtood in <hi>greateſt</hi>
need of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But, ſay they, we can <hi>better</hi> employ
our time at <hi>home,</hi> and <hi>read</hi> good Books, and <hi>better</hi>
Sermons than our <hi>Miniſters</hi> can make. And in theſe <hi>ſtudied
Excuſes,</hi> take themſelves to be no leſs <hi>zealous,</hi> but onely
more <hi>diſcreet</hi> than their Brethren, who do not the like; when indeed
they are guilty of <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs:</hi> Of <hi>folly,</hi>
in aſcribing as great applauſe to our <hi>private</hi> Devotions (which
loſe their <hi>vertue,</hi> and have no promiſe of <hi>audience,</hi> being
done in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to God's publick Worſhip) as the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Oriſons of religiouſly diſpoſed perſons in Gods Houſe of Prayer:
And of <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> in offering <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> 
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:99495:59"/> for <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> robbing God of one duty, and
paying him with another; with-holding the <hi>greater,</hi> and yet would
ſeem conſcientious in the <hi>leſs.</hi> Whilſt thus contemning the
<hi>Precepts</hi> of Heaven, and the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> in doing
their <hi>own</hi> Will, they loſe the benefit of both: <hi>Who hath
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired theſe things at your hand?</hi> Religion is not a thing left to the
<hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary</hi> fancies of men, to cull out from that <hi>diverſity</hi>
with which the World abounds, what beſt pleaſes themſelves; neither are
the <hi>ways</hi> and mediums of the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of it, put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their
power; but as <hi>God</hi> is the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Worſhip, ſo the <hi>means</hi>
and <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> by which, and how he is <hi>honoured,</hi> and his
Servants <hi>benefited,</hi> muſt be circumſtantiated by himſelf;
<hi>his</hi> Will, and not <hi>ours,</hi> muſt be the ſole and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equate
Rule. All Ordinances do not work <hi>neceſſarily,</hi> as the Sun
enlightens the ſable Skies; nor <hi>phyſically,</hi> as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an
<hi>inherent</hi> power to produce their effects: but they are operative by the
<hi>ſacredneſs of their Inſtitution.</hi> Be wiſe then, O Chriſtians,
in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a <hi>venerable</hi> eſteem of our <hi>Church</hi> devotions,
where God by <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn <pb n="109" facs="tcp:99495:59"/> Prayer</hi> is invoked,
<hi>the Word preached,</hi> and <hi>the Sacraments rightly and reverendly
adminiſtred;</hi> being <hi>as Babes for hunger and thirſt after them,</hi>
though not for knowledge and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in them. 'Tis a no leſs
<hi>common</hi> than <hi>dreadful</hi> obſervation, that thoſe that leave
the <hi>Church-Aſſemblies,</hi> do at laſt bid adieu to <hi>Religion</hi>
alſo: Which that we may prevent, 'tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient <hi>we forſake not the
aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is,</hi> but
account it a ſpecial favour from God, when we may <hi>congregate</hi> our
ſelves <hi>freely</hi> to <hi>worſhip the God of our Fathers.</hi> And that
our obedience may keep pace with the mercy, let us provoke one another to the
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this duty, ſaying, <hi>Come, let us go up to the mountain of
the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Jacob, to pray before the Lord, and with
praiſes make his Name glorious.</hi> But alas, we might rather expect the
<hi>removal</hi> of this <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> than the continuance thereof,
for our exceeding <hi>faultineſs</hi> and <hi>negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</hi> God hath
given a long and happy reſt to the Land of our Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with advantages of
giving our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance at <hi>the poſts of the doors of the 
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:99495:60"/> Lords houſe:</hi> We are not driven, like the Primitive
Chriſtians, <hi>of whom the world was not worthy,</hi> to aſſemble by
ſtealth in Dens and Caves of the Earth, being perſecuted, afflicted, and
tormented; but the Gates of the <hi>Lords Houſe</hi> have been open to us,
and we have or might have had free acceſs <hi>to his Altars.</hi> While other
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have heard the terrible noiſe of <hi>Cannons,</hi> and the
<hi>diſmal</hi> effects of War and <hi>Bloud-ſhed,</hi> the ſhreeks of
<hi>Widows</hi> and <hi>Orphans,</hi> we have had the muſick of Bells calling
us to the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> and there the melody of <hi>Pſalms, and
Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs.</hi> We read in <hi>Acts</hi> 9.31. that <hi>the
Churches had reſt through all Judea;</hi> and what uſe did they make
thereof? Did they grow <hi>careleſs</hi> and <hi>wanton,</hi> kick againſt
the <hi>Breaſts</hi> that gave them ſuck, and ſpurn at thoſe
<hi>Knees</hi> whereon they were dandled? Did they <hi>contemn</hi>
Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, <hi>ſlight</hi> the Sacraments, <hi>throw contempt</hi> upon
Prayer, and <hi>deſpiſe</hi> Prophecying? Did they loſe their <hi>first
love,</hi> and neglect the <hi>good oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities</hi> which God gave them for
their increaſe in Holineſs? No, <hi>they were edified, and walked in the
fear of the Lord, and were multiplied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:99495:60"/>Oh let us follow theſe pious Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, in
loving the place <hi>where Gods honour dwels,</hi> and anſwering the end for
which they were appointed. He that frequents the place of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, hath
an <hi>early</hi> Title to a <hi>Bleſſing:</hi> for though many are found
of God that <hi>ſought him not,</hi> yet few or none ever <hi>ſought</hi>
him but they ſhall find him, though it be in the laſt Watch of the night:
Nay, ſometimes thoſe who have had <hi>ill deſignes</hi> in going to
Church, yet God hath made it <hi>work for their good,</hi> and of unwilling
Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, framed willing and real Converts. St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in a proud
humour of carping, entred the Church of St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> but departed
with a broken and bleeding heart: And who can tell but God may work as great a
change on you, if you would not fly the means that God hath appointed, and
wilfully neglect ſo great Salvation?</p>
            <p>Let us at laſt, with the ſhrill Cock, not onely awake others,
but clap our own ſides. A <hi>ſinning Prieſt</hi> is the fall of many,
and the offence of all: It was a lamentable ſight in the Prophets eye, that
the very <hi>ſtones of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary were ſtumbling-blocks in every
ſtreet.</hi> 
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:99495:61"/> What doth embolden ſin more? what doth
occaſion more ſpiritual falls, than the <hi>foul Example</hi> of a
Church-man? who is heavenly in his Pulpit onely, but out of it given to all
exceſs of riot. Oh how <hi>barbarouſly</hi> and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly do they wound
<hi>the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus,</hi> that preach it to the World, yet
live as if they intended to go to Heaven ſome other way <hi>than that which
they teach their Auditors!</hi> Nay, how is it poſſible his diſcourſes
againſt ſin, and of Heaven and Hell, ſhould prevail to the <hi>amendment
of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> who hath no care of his <hi>own Soul?</hi> for the love men
have to their Vices, with a little help from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, will eaſily
perſwade them the whole is <hi>fictitious,</hi> or elſe that Heaven may be
obtained, and Hell eſcaped, upon eaſier terms than the Prieſt tells them.
How odious is the name of ſome <hi>old Heretick</hi> that hath fill'd the
Church with Garboils and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy? yet a <hi>crafty Heretick,</hi> in St.
<hi>Bernard</hi>'s account, hurts leſs than a <hi>leud Miniſter:</hi> for
Hereticks poyſon the Church but with Words, with giddy Tenents, and airy
Speculations, which vulgar heads are not capable of; <pb n="113" facs="tcp:99495:61"/> but
each ſhallow Ideot will ſpy a <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order</hi> in our lives, and
ſooner follow our <hi>Vices,</hi> than maintain our <hi>Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
Divines may not think to carry it as ſome more wittily than truly ſay
<hi>Phyſitians</hi> do, to have the <hi>Sun</hi> ſee their good deeds, and
the <hi>grave</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcond their failures. No, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, in the very
walls of your houſes holes will be dig'd (as in the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of
<hi>Ezekiel</hi>) <hi>to ſpy out your ſecret a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominations;</hi> we cannot
erre, but with the Snail, we leave our ſlimy filth to publick view; and what
need we wonder, that our <hi>Meſſages miſcarry,</hi> and that the
following ſlock are <hi>tumbling down,</hi> when their <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd</hi> is
walking on the <hi>edge of Rocks!</hi> The River <hi>Nilus,</hi> as
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us, hath a marvellous Stone in it, which if ground
to powder, and given to a dog in ſome proper Vehicle, he will never be able
to ſpend his mouth. Beloved, that harſh and auſtere life, as it were the
Stone of <hi>Nile,</hi> if we ſoften it in liquor and voluptuous courſes,
we quite loſe the vigor of our rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king voice, the authority of our holy
Embaſſie! What do we <hi>ſweating in Pulpits,</hi> if we love and
practiſe the <pb n="98" facs="tcp:99495:62"/> Vices we declaim againſt! Divinity is a
ſtrange kind of Phyſick, that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects no Cure, unleſs the
<hi>Phyſician</hi> take it as well as the <hi>Patient.</hi> Who pulls a
drowning man out of a deep ſtream with a dry hand? <hi>Joaſh</hi> his Arrow
is then prevalent, <hi>when the Prophets Arm is joyned to it.</hi> A merry
Souldier ſtruck a bird dead, from which his Comrades expected an Augury;
ſaying, <hi>How ſhould theſe ſilly creatures direct others, that
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſecure themſelves?</hi> Who goes to a Barber for his bread, or to a
Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler for his cloth? and who will e're hope to receive direction for
Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from them, in whom there is nothing to be ſeen but Vice? We often
complain, and it may be juſtly enough, of prevailing Faction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us;
but I am ſure nothing ſo much promotes their intereſt, as the
<hi>ſcandalous lives</hi> of ſome that exerciſe the Miniſterial
Function among us. The late incomparable Biſhop, Dr. <hi>Jer. Taylor,</hi>
tells us,<note place="margin">Sermon to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of
<hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </note> If we live Holy, our Doctrine will be true, and that
truth ſhall prevail: but if we live <hi>Wickedly and Scandalouſly,</hi>
every little Schiſmatick will put us to ſhame, <pb n="115" facs="tcp:99495:62"/> and
abuſe our Flocks, and feed them with Colocynths and Hemlock; and place
Hereſie in the Chair oppointed for our Religion. 'Tis an errour I know, a
<hi>fond</hi> and <hi>preciſe</hi> errour, to think the Power of Gods Word,
or the benefit of the Sacrament, ſhould be tied to the holineſs of <hi>him
that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistereth.</hi> The Church in the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> is a Garden of
Nuts:<note place="margin">Cant. 6.11</note> and if the Law of God that is planted
here, be a Nut, we may ſafely eat the Kernel, though it come from a ſlovens
hand. But truly it were to be wiſhed, that as the beautiful Heavens above our
heads, are infinitely rais'd from earth, moſt different and oppoſite to her
Centre; ſo the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of Heaven were as far remov'd from the
baſe and <hi>ſinful</hi> cuſtomes of this corrupt World, that inſtead
of refreſhing Fountains, they were not Whirlpools to draw into danger ſuch
as are about them: For as the <hi>Ivy</hi> and <hi>Elm,</hi> for the
<hi>People</hi> and <hi>Paſtor</hi> grow together: <hi>The people,</hi>
ſaith <hi>Jeremy, take ill courſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer.
23.10.</note> and the reaſon is added in the next words: <hi>The Prophet and
Prieſt are profane men.</hi> Therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> thought it would ask
more than an ordinary care;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.17</note> that 
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:99495:63"/> it would be a point of high prudence in us, to be
<hi>honeſt</hi> men, not onely in the ſight of <hi>God,</hi> but in the
eyes of the <hi>World</hi> alſo. Even Kings and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours have refuſed to
quench their extreme thirſt with offered Water, when their Armies had none:
they would not give an <hi>example of Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance:</hi> Why then do they that
are <hi>Sacred to God,</hi> offer themſelves up to ſwiniſh exceſſes,
with the <hi>hazard</hi> of ſo many <hi>Souls?</hi> The Whale eſpying her
young ones at a low water, left in danger of the almoſt-dry ſhore, ſpouts
ſuch abundance of water upon them, that they can ſwim away in that
ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Tide.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nat.</note> Did we truly regard the <hi>welfare</hi> of the Servants
of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> we would part with our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, to <hi>ſave
their</hi> Souls; we would abandon our delights, we would caſt out a drunken
humour, to bring them again into the right way: and this we may learn from the
<hi>Indian Ocotochlus,</hi> that having obtained his Prey by a great noiſe,
invites other beaſts to feed on it; and when they are ſated, feeds on the
reſt, that the poyſon wherewith he abounds, might not injure his
meſ-mates by feeding <pb n="117" facs="tcp:99495:63"/> with them. What a ſhame is this
to us men! to us <hi>conſecrated Prieſts!</hi> that will abſtain from
none of our Cups, from none of our Carouſes, from none of our vain delights,
how <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> how infecting ſoever.</p>
            <p>Truly, the beſt remedy I can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto us of the
<hi>Clergy,</hi> who are <hi>ſet upon a hill,</hi> for religious
<hi>Example,</hi> or the peoples <hi>Scorn</hi> and <hi>Deriſion,</hi> is a
holy <hi>Privacy and Retiredneſs;</hi> at leaſt a <hi>careful</hi> choice
of our <hi>Company.</hi> It is on record in <hi>Leviticus</hi> 14.36. <hi>That
the Prieſts of God must not come into a polluted houſe.</hi> They that are
ſtrangers to the <hi>courſe</hi> of our lives, will judge of us by the
<hi>quality</hi> of our company. We looſe our maſculine Gravity, and get
<hi>contempt</hi> by <hi>Familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> We throw the <hi>Honour</hi> of our
<hi>Function</hi> too prodigally into a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon boſome,</hi> whiles we
are ſeen mixing at <hi>Feaſts</hi> and merry meetings with <hi>light and
diſſolute</hi> perſons. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is obſerved never to ſtay long
at <hi>Capernaum:</hi> it was a place of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and, as
<hi>Druthmarus</hi> tells us, was much haunted for that purpoſe, even by the
Grandees of <hi>Rome.</hi> People are prone to take <hi>offence</hi> that
<hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> 
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:99495:64"/> ſhould ſhare in thoſe
pleaſures, or haunt thoſe places, which yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves will freely
enjoy. The damned Churl thought he muſt be a man of <hi>another world,</hi>
that could convert his brethren. How ſhall Souldiers wound their enemies, if
their Battalion ſtand not aloof? how ſhall we vanquiſh humane
corruptions, if we keep not from them? St. <hi>Paul wiſhed himſelf
ſeparate even from Chriſt, for his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſake;</hi> and ſhall not
we ſeparate from leud and debauched Societies, for as great a matters doth it
not hinder <hi>men</hi> in the way of Salvation to be inſenſible of their
own errings? and who will think that he goes <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray,</hi> while his
<hi>Paſtor</hi> is in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany? ſhould no ſcandal enſue, yet we
pull a ſtain upon our ſelves: For he that ſorts with uncivil men, ſhall
hardly come off untainted.</p>
            <p>While the Hebrew Multitude <hi>ſports</hi> and <hi>dances,</hi>
and worſhips a <hi>gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf, Moſes</hi> is on the Mount with God,
<hi>praying</hi> and <hi>weeping,</hi> and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding for the ſins of the
people Let the <hi>world</hi> take her courſe, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue her follies it
is not for us, my <hi>holy Brethren,</hi> it is not for us to mix with 
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:99495:64"/> it: it would become us better to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and pray and
weep for <hi>publick offences:</hi> not to lie as <hi>ſtumbling-blocks,</hi>
and pull Gods anger upon us; but to <hi>ſtand in the gap, and turn away his
wrathful Indignation:</hi> This were the way to be held in <hi>greater
account,</hi> if we were leſs ſeen; to be more conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous, if we were
more hidden; if like the <hi>Halcyon</hi> birds, we came not out but to calm a
tempeſtuous, Sea, to remove troubles, and to bring peace to the vexed
Conſcience. <hi>Woe be to them that gad abroad on contrary errands,</hi> even
to raiſe ſtirs, and to cauſe offences. <hi>Vae Sacerdoti,</hi> wo be to
the Church-man, by whoſe irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Life the offence comes.</p>
            <p>A <hi>ſinful complyance</hi> with the humors of Factious people,
againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Order of Holy Church, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother offence in
<hi>Clergy-men;</hi> and too many ſuch <hi>falſe brethren</hi> there are
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. I ſpeak this to their ſhame, who like <hi>Ariſtotles</hi>
firſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are capable of any form which profit ſhall ſtamp upon
them, and will be any thing, but what <hi>they ought to be:</hi> for in
declaiming againſt abuſes, their meaning is not to have them 
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:99495:65"/> redreſſed, but by diſgracing the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
poſture of things, to make a way for their own exploded Diſcipline; it
being a certain Rule, that he which perſwades a multitude that things are not
as they ought to be, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver want <hi>Rewards,</hi> nor
<hi>Auditors;</hi> becauſe under this fair and plauſible colour,
whatſoever they utter paſſeth for good and currant: Theſe are the
ſeeming friends that do more hurt to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than her
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed enemies: For open force is not ſo dangerous, as cloſe
diſſimulation. In which reſpect it may be truly ſaid of our Church,
what is ſpoken of the Eagle in the Greek Apologue,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that died with the greater
horrour, becauſe ſhe received her mortal Wound, with a Dart which was
winged with a Feather of her own kind. Theſe <hi>ſerve not the Lord
Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, but their own belly,</hi> who creep to the Altar to devour
the Church's Morſels, whilſt privately they cry, <hi>Down with it, down
with it, even to the ground.</hi> And though by Subſcription they have given
us an aſſurance of their Submiſſion, yet by conforming with a
<hi>grudging conſcience, <pb n="121" facs="tcp:99495:65"/> out of neceſſity, and not
with a ready mind,</hi> do more undermine the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Impoſitions, than the
Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts themſelves. They were unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in their Education, and (to
prove they are like <hi>glaſs,</hi> which once being crack'd, does ever
remain craz'd and unſound) do continue obſtinate and incorrigible, in their
ſneaking obnun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations: and accordingly when they are called to execute the
Miniſterial Function, if they may do it ſafely, and without cenſure, 'tis
ordinary without any remorſe, to the great <hi>ſcandal</hi> of poor people,
and the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them in their Errours, upon all occaſions, to neglect the
<hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the Church: as for inſtance, if a zealous and
<hi>rich Male-content</hi> deſires the Baptiſm of his Child may not be
accompanied with <hi>the Sign of the Croſs,</hi> it ſhall, to pleaſe this
Opinioniſt, be cenſured as a Romiſh uſe, and omitted accordingly;
though the Incumbent is ſenſible, that very act renders him Perjured in the
wilful breach of his Oath of Canonical Obedience. If a ſick perſon intreats
the Prayers of the Congregation, the Office of the Church for that purpoſe
ſhall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected <pb n="106" facs="tcp:99495:66"/> in the Desk, to ſhew how far the
<hi>Mimick</hi> can exceed the Churches preſcription in his
<hi>Extemporary</hi> abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Pulpit, And becauſe the common
Devotions of the Church muſt precede the Sermon, they ſhall be ſo
irreverently hurryed over, that the people may eaſily perceive the
<hi>Heteroclite</hi> performs them not as Prayers, but as an impoſed Task,
<hi>for which he mourns in ſecret.</hi> Theſe are the ſlights which our
Semiconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts uſe, to ſecure the good Opinion of the Factious, and to
ſtigmatize their Zealous brethren with the Name of <hi>Rigid
Conformiſts,</hi> who but conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably perform what they apprehend to be
their Duty. This gives us cauſe to complain with the Prophet, that <hi>the
Leaders of the people cauſe them to erre,</hi> and deſerve to be
<hi>ſharply rebuked, that they may be ſound in the Faith, and not
toſſed to &amp; fro with every wind of popular oblimation.</hi> For though
they applaud themſelves with the gilded title of <hi>moderate Men,</hi> they
are in plain and true Engliſh, the <hi>Peſt</hi> and <hi>Bane</hi> of our
Church, whoſe <hi>ambodex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> contributes not to the
<hi>ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of the Edifice, but to the <hi>demoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing</hi> of
the Fabrick</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:99495:66"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But did not
St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhort men to Moderation by his own example, when he became
<hi>all things to all men, that he might gain ſome?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The ſum of theſe words, ſo
often and erroniouſly brought to juſtifie this <hi>omnifarious
principle,</hi> imports no more than this, that he denyed himſelf in the
<hi>uſe</hi> of his liberty, to gain thoſe that were not acquainted with
the <hi>extent</hi> of it; and dealt with all ſorts of men in that way, which
he thought moſt probable to convert them to Chriſtianity, and keep them in
the regular profeſſion of it: Not that he <hi>ſneaked</hi> and
<hi>diſſembled,</hi> and made weak people think that he was of their mind;
and ſo <hi>confirmed</hi> them in their <hi>miſtakes</hi> and
<hi>follies:</hi> Nor had he any regard to the humours of
<hi>unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> and meerly <hi>captious</hi> people, that will be
finding faults upon no ground at all: this muſt needs be <hi>unworthy of an
Apoſtle;</hi> for it is ſo of all inferiour <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and
likewiſe of every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtian. Let me therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you, my
brethren, who are too guilty in this particular, not to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice your
<hi>Souls</hi> to your <hi>Fortunes,</hi> nor repair a
<hi>ſubſiſtence</hi> with the leaſt breach <pb n="124" facs="tcp:99495:67"/> of
your <hi>Conſciences:</hi> But for time to come approve your ſelves
faithful, by employing your beſt diligence to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the judgment of others,
(eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe that ſeem to have your Perſons in admiration)
concerning the Nature and Uſe of thoſe things they oppoſe with ſo much
fury; and not humour them in their petulant diſlikes, and pernicious errours;
nor ſuffer them to continue therein with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your rebukes, either publick, or
private, as prudence ſhall direct, and opportunity miniſter occaſion: and
this will be a means to pacifie the <hi>God</hi> you have <hi>angered,</hi> the
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> you have <hi>grieved,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> that you
have <hi>wronged,</hi> and your <hi>Souls</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> whom you
have <hi>offended. Voe Semi-chriſtiani,</hi> woe to the partial Conformiſt,
by whoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful compliance the offence comes.</p>
            <p>There be little ones in the Family too; little ones in a literal
ſenſe, ſuch as our Saviour was now pointing unto: and here I muſt bring
you forth the <hi>Guardians</hi> of Youth, <hi>Parents,</hi> and
<hi>Poedagogues,</hi> and <hi>Heads</hi> of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, who either by negligent
nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or naughty examples, are guilty <pb n="125" facs="tcp:99495:67"/> of an
<hi>Offence.</hi> What an offence was it in <hi>Noahs</hi> Family, to ſee the
old man ſo drown'd in his exceſs! How is <hi>Cham</hi> heightned with
ſcorn and deriſion, <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet</hi> dejected with ſhame
and grief, at the ill example of their aged Father.</p>
            <p>As water follows the track of your fingers end, ſo young
children with the leaſt word or deed, are drawn away: <hi>I ſpeak that
which I have ſeen with my Father, and you do that which you have ſeen with
your father,</hi> ſaith our bleſſed Saviour.<note place="margin">John
8.38.</note> How ready are chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to do that which they ſee done by their
Parents! Beware therefore, all you that have attained this <hi>Reverend</hi>
Name, that you let not your children ſee you do or ſpeak, that which they
cannot do or ſpeak after you, but they muſt ſin.</p>
            <p>The moſt powerful motive to ſin, and that which maketh a
forcible entry into the Soul, is Vice armed with the authority of a Parent; be
it Lying, Swearing, Drinking, or Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that uſual, though dangerous Sport,
which doth not ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create, as infect them with all ill cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, of
lying, and couzenage, and the like abominations</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:99495:68"/>Many times, on the other hand, Parents
corrupt their children with too much <hi>indulgence</hi> and mildneſs towards
them, never finding in their hearts to chaſtize them, upon a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
conceit, they are too near our bloods to be controuled. What! do not vermine,
and other ſuperfluities proceed from our own bodies, yet being noyſome are
caſt forth? How ſhall <hi>Amaleck</hi> be chaſed away, if the Rod of
<hi>Moſes</hi> be not lifted up? How ſhall growing corruptions be rooted
out, when Diſcipline and due cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection are laid aſide? it was this
plunged King <hi>David</hi> in a world of Woe; for cockering one of his Sons,
he felt the loſs of two: Had <hi>Amnon</hi> been chid by his Father, he had
not perhaps been murthered by his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Yet ſo far are many from
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving theſe things, that they rather cheriſh them in their faults,
hearing their leud words with applauſe and ſmiling, as the tokens of a
pregnant Nature; which fond <hi>indulgence,</hi> as it is ſtill
<hi>pernicious</hi> to children, by unſinew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their minds and bodies into
all kind of Luxuary, ſo it proveth many times no leſs diſaſtrous unto
Parents, <pb n="111" facs="tcp:99495:68"/> who are commonly moſt grieved with thoſe
whom they breed moſt wantonly: Then feeling the ſad truth of
<hi>Syracides</hi> his Obſervation, <hi>Cocker thy child and he ſhall make
thee afraid, play with him and he will bring thee to heavineſs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 30.9.</note> He that will let his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren alone till
they have <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Animum conſilio
ac ratione firmatum,</hi> a fixed and ſetled judgment, ſhall find evil
habits ſo fixt and permanent, that good counſel will be too eaſie a
remedy.</p>
            <p>'Tis another offence in point of Nurture, that they who would not
lay the Fruit of their Orchards on a dank floor where it would rot and
putrifie, will yet ſuffer the Fruit of their Loyns to be depraved and
corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted in <hi>bad company,</hi> which is the plague &amp; bane of all
Goodneſs; whoſe poyſonous leaven more infecteth, and ſinketh deeper
into the ſoul, than all the precepts of Virtue and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs can do on the
contrary: Such Parents are like the <hi>Eſtrich</hi> that is hardned
againſt her young ones; who provide not for their children <hi>the ſincere
Milk of the Word, that they might grow thereby:</hi> But from the 
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:99495:69"/> time of their being waſht in the Laver of Regeneration,
take no more care, but expoſe them forthwith to ſuch luſts &amp;
converſations, as are much more wild and ſavage than thoſe beaſts<note n="*" place="margin">Lam. 4.3. Job. 39.14.</note> in the compariſon; to which
they cannot chooſe but be a prey. They ſtrive indeed (as the
<hi>moding</hi> term is), to educate them into <hi>men</hi> betimes; that is,
make them <hi>converſible</hi> and <hi>bold:</hi> and ſince for that they
muſt engage them into frequent company, where they ſee and hear mens
follies, that I ſay no worſe, by that means they come to have their
underſtandings ſtored with nothing but the modes and ſins of
Converſation; filled with froth and mud, for want of religious prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
being inſtill'd and wrought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their minds <hi>before theſe evil days
came on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis another offence in point of Nurture, that young ones for
durty reſpects are forced to a courſe of life either in the Church or
Kingdome, which they neither affect, nor are fit for. A man would think the
maid that let in St. <hi>Peter</hi> to a warm Hall, and a good fire in a cold
night, had done him an high curteſie, but it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <pb n="129" facs="tcp:99495:69"/> a
manifeſt injury: for that very maid drew him firſt to the foul ſin which
he ſhortly after commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. So men think they have fairly acquitted
themſelves in Offices of love and care, if they can bring up a child to be a
Scholar. Nay, the violence of ſome rigorous Pedant (who, I verily think, is
as deep in our Saviours wo, as any other) ſhall make him one whether he will
or no: and now an Advowſon is bought for him, <hi>the maid hath opened the
door:</hi> world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly policy and covetouſneſs hath brought the youngſter
into the <hi>high Prieſts Hall to the fire-ſide;</hi> but how oft doth
ſin and offences follow! your Scholar perhaps hath neither body nor brain fit
for his Function; and then like cruel <hi>Palamedes,</hi> you have but laid
your child before <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> Plough to be run over; or like our
Lords Tempter, you have but led him up to the <hi>Pinacle</hi> of the
<hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> to get a fall. This might have been prevented, if you had gone
to work like the old <hi>Spartans;</hi> they would feel the palms of a mans
hand, whether they were hard or ſoft, whether he were like to be a painful
man, ere <pb n="130" facs="tcp:99495:70"/> they would chooſe him into a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Office.
We ſhould do as much in the tryal of <hi>Wits</hi> and <hi>Inclinations,</hi>
ere we mark out a little one for his profeſſion: for many times the
King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is robbed of a <hi>good artificer,</hi> and the Church over-charg'd
with a <hi>bad Miniſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Heads of Families 'tis an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence that there is no more care
took of a Servants Soul: the Maſter 
<note n="*" place="margin">Gent. Calling.</note> impoſes his Vices
upon his whole Family, as if they were to be the badges and cognizances to
witneſs whom they belonged to; as if they thought it a diſparagement to
their qualities, to go to Hell without an honourable Retinue. Hence
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and drunkenneſs are winked at, as if they made for the Maſters
cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; as if Bounty could not be ſeen but in a Deluge, or Hoſpitality
ſtood in ſtaggering; that many of them are wholly kept with Kitchin
drudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery, or wordly employment, from the ſervice of God. <hi>Voe patri, Voe
patri familiâs, Voe lactantibus!</hi> woe be them that give ſuck, if
they bring up their babes no better; woe to the Parent, to the good man of the
houſe, by <pb n="131" facs="tcp:99495:70"/> whoſe ill example or looſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
the <hi>offence</hi> comes.</p>
            <p>There are offences we ſee in the <hi>fails of Superiours,</hi>
there are offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces too in <hi>the fails of the religious.</hi> As pilferers
regard not empty Cottages, but prey and break into rich houſes to rob and
ſpoil; ſo that cunning tempter beſtirs himſelf moſt to rifle ſuch
hearts as are richly fraught with the graces of God: and many times his
deſire is attained; for through thoſe <hi>relicks of corruption</hi> that
ſtill reſide in the beſt of us, we are too prone to ſtumble into the
paths of ſin. Certainly, Religion it ſelf getteth a blot in the fall of a
juſt man; how is the Name of the Lord blaſphemed, when the <hi>man after
his own heart is found an Adulterer?</hi> let him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>that thinks he
ſtands</hi> ſure, let him that <hi>profeſſes the Name of Chriſt</hi>
with zeal and ardour, <hi>let him take heed leſt he fall,</hi> leſt the
prophane <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins</hi> rejoyce, and uncircumciſed hearts triumph
over goodneſs it ſelf, in the fall of her zealous Votary.</p>
            <p>None ſo much detriment Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as thoſe that profeſs a
believing in Chriſt, but in their converſations <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny 
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:99495:71"/> the Lord that bought them.</hi> Now what is this, but to
act the Heathen under the Honourable name of a Chriſtian, and offend more
heinouſly for being inveſted with that Sacred Title? as the higher our
Prerogative is, ſo much the greater is our fault. The very Religion we
profeſs, is an aggravation to our ſins; <hi>he that knows his Maſters
will,</hi> and ſquares not his life accordingly, does but load his Soul with
the greater guilt and more intolerable puniſhment. There may be ſome
excuſe for ignorance, but the contemptuous and wilful ſins of
profeſſors, will not obtain an eaſie pardon; <hi>to him that knoweth to
do good, and doth it not, to him it is ſin.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam.
4.17.</note> With what face can we look up and call our ſelves by Chriſts
Name, who are ſhamefully upbraided by the practice of a <hi>Pericles,
Socrates,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtides,</hi> who are accounted Heathens and
Barbarous? what prodigies of baſeneſs do we Chriſtians make our ſelves,
upon the account of our <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous practices,</hi> whoſe holy Religion
laies undiſpenſible obligations upon its followers, only to think upon and
to do <hi>whatſoever things are honeſt, <pb n="133" facs="tcp:99495:71"/> whatſoever
things are juſt, whatſoever are of good report:</hi> and it is heartily to
be wiſhed, that men would not pride themſelves in the <hi>miſtaken</hi>
ſigns of Grace, and think their condition good, only becauſe they have
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded themſelves to believe ſo; but would endeavour to be <hi>true
and real Chriſtians,</hi> that the Name of God and Religion be not evil
ſpoken of for their miſcarriages.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Men and Women offend one another, <hi>by that wanton
garb of Apparel they have taken up.</hi> Light Weeds I know are accounted but a
ſlender fault, but why ſhould not our Pulpits arraign that which
<hi>Eſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> did? how doth that noble Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet lift up his voice like a
trumpet, proclaiming an heavy woe to thoſe <hi>that draw iniquity with cords
of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> To ſteal a ſilken ſtring were no great Robbery; but how
if a rowe of Diamonds hung upon it? how if on theſe things we count but light
and vain toyes, monſtrous iniquities do depend? Pride and haughtineſs,
oppreſſion and envy, ſcandal and luſt, what goodly Patrimonies do they
not exhauſt? what works of mercy <pb n="134" facs="tcp:99495:72"/> do they not devour?
what honeſt eyes do they not offend? what hearts do they not batter? O God,
what do we mean to indanger one another? why do we kindle the flame of Luſt
in anothers boſome? ſhould our own hearts be innocent, yet we draw
ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition and envy upon our ſelves. Our bleſſed Saviour would have
us <hi>wiſe as Serpents,</hi> and 'tis a piece of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents wiſdom,
that coming abroad to drink, he leaves his poyſon at home, leſt other
Creatures periſh by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that drink at the ſame Spring. Let us,
my brethren, be thus wiſe; does any <hi>infectious evil</hi> reſide in our
Souls, any <hi>poyſon of Aſps</hi> lurk un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our tongues, any <hi>foul
enormity</hi> appear in our lives, any <hi>unjuſt violence</hi> defile our
hands, any <hi>ſcandalous Weeds</hi> hang on our backs; either ſpit your
poyſon out, or ſo ſmother it, that it hurt none but thy ſelf. Was not
young <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> even then an happy man,
when he was turned out to the wide world, when he was fain to forſake his
Countrey, and Friends, and his Fathers houſe? how happy a Voyage did that
forlorn wanderer make, that thus ſaved his <pb n="135" facs="tcp:99495:72"/> own life,
and his Brothers innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy? get thee gone, O man, get thee gone from thy
brothers ſight, if there be ought in thee <hi>that offendeth his eye, or
woundeth his Soul;</hi> and that for <hi>thy brothers ſake, for thy Saviours
ſake, for thy own ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for thy Brothers ſake: for by thine offenſive
carriage <hi>thy weak Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther periſheth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor.
8.10.</note> Methinks every word is a new enforcement; offend him not, for he
is <hi>thy Brother;</hi> offend him not, becauſe <hi>he is weak;</hi> offend
him not, becauſe <hi>he periſheth by it.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> that
ſought our Saviours life, would be thought <hi>Abrahams</hi> Children; but
Chriſt fetcheth their Pedegree from Hell; <hi>they are of their father the
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who was a Murtherer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh.
8.44.</note> How was the Devil a Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer? he came not with a Sword or
Poniard at his ſide, but whiſpered a wicked word, and killed us all: he
killed our bodies, he killed our Souls too, when our fore-fathers were tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to ſin. Now if thoſe that ſought the bodily death of our Saviour, were in
this the brats of that murderous Feind, how can we think better of them that
ſeek the deſtruction of <pb n="136" facs="tcp:99495:73"/> Souls, ſince it was of the
Soul too that <hi>the Devil was a Murtherer from the beginning?</hi> By killing
a man, thou doſt but rob him of that <hi>Breath</hi> which is common to him
with other Creatures; but by leading him into a vicious courſe, thou
ſtrippeſt his <hi>Soul</hi> of that life of Grace, which the Angels of
Heaven are more happy in than in their natural being: mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the
<hi>Body,</hi> and thou takeſt but his <hi>Soul</hi> from it; but miſlead
his <hi>Soul,</hi> and thou takeſt away his <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As for thy brothers ſake, ſo <hi>for thy Saviours
ſake too,</hi> take heed of offences, leſt thy weak Brother pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for
whom Chriſt dyed. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, O Man, ſaith holy <hi>Bernard,</hi> if the
Son of God gave up his pretious Blood to redeem the Souls of men, do not they
perſecute him worſe, who rob him of his <hi>purchaſed Souls,</hi> than
the <hi>Jews</hi> did, who ſhed his pretious Blood? 'tis one of the Laws of
God, that if a ſtack of Corn, or Corn-field, had been burnt up, he that
kindled the fire was to make amends for the loſs. For a whole year the poor
Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman had took pains for that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> creaſe; but it was not one, nor <pb n="137" facs="tcp:99495:73"/> two, nor
three, but thirty three years together, that the Son of God labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hard to
get a crop of Souls into his Garner: what fearful <hi>Agonies</hi> did he go
through! what a <hi>bloody ſweat</hi> bedewed his face, that theſe fruits
might proſper and grow! and rather than go without this fruit, he would give
his life for it: every Chriſtian Soul is (as it were) a ſheaf of this
harveſt, which after ſo many toylſome endeavours of that careful
Husbandman to bring it to maturity, if thou ſhalt now ſcorch and burn up,
by miſ-leading a man firſt into the crooked paths of ſin, and at laſt
plunge him into the unquenchable flames of Hell; hath not the Lord of the
Harveſt Reaſon to look theſe conſumed ſheaves, this ſpoyled crop,
this waſtful detriment ſhould be made good? and how this reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
ſhould be made, God Almighty hath directed in another caſe: <hi>If a man
dig or open a pit, and an Ox or an Aſs fall therein, the owner of the pit
ſhall reſtore the price of the beaſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod.
21.33.</note> By drawing thy brother to ſin, thou haſt opened a
<hi>bottomleſs pit,</hi> in which his Soul is everlaſtingly plunged: and 
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:99495:74"/> ſince thou canſt not reſtore that peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Soul,
thou muſt be accountable to God <hi>for the price of it;</hi> and what was
the price of thy Brothers Soul, but the pretious blood of the Son of God? let
me intreat you therefore to conſider in time, that it is no petty driblet, no
trifling arrearage thou runneſt into, but it is thoſe <hi>invaluable drops
of thy Saviours Blood</hi> thou art now guilty of: and with what pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
can'ſt thou wipe out ſuch a ſcore! why, if there be none elſe, it
muſt be ſuch a recompence as the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law exacted, <hi>a
life for a life, an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth, a burning for a
burning, a wound for a wound.</hi> Haſt thou been an helper of thy Brothers
deſtruction? a Soul muſt go for a Soul, a burning for a burning; thou that
haſt brought his Soul with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reach of thoſe endleſs torments,
canſt look for no leſs to be <hi>the portion of thine inheritance,</hi>
than to be caſt ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recoverably into the mercileſs and devouring flames of
Gods everlaſting diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For thy own ſake, give no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: for as
<hi>Moſes</hi> loads him with fearful curſes, that ſhall <hi>remove the 
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:99495:74"/> bounds of his Neighbours land;</hi> ſo the Law of God
hath fenc'd in the Souls of men; and he that makes them common, which that
Divine rule had incloſed, ſtands liable to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven curſes of the Son
of God, <hi>woe be to that man;</hi> and thus we find it of old: for as they
that intend to deſtroy any devouring beaſts of prey, can do it no better
way than by kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thoſe that are great with young; ſo Almighty God hath
always took vengeance on the Parents and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of ſin, that he might root
out the young cubs in their Dams belly.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Jews</hi> were conſulting what to do with him that
gathered ſticks on their Sabbath-day, Gods O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle inſtructed them <hi>to
ſtone him to death,</hi> becauſe (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> ſtates it, though
the fault in it ſelf were a light one) he was <hi>the firſt that offended
in this kind:</hi> the firſt man that violated that Sacred Law, &amp; in his
miſ-leading act, as in the Womb of a ſhe-Wolf, the future
tranſgreſſions of others lay bleeding. For this cauſe, when that vile
Traytor <hi>Judas</hi> had hang'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>his bowels guſh'd out on
the ground,</hi> becauſe he was the <hi>firſt</hi> man that laid 
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:99495:75"/> wicked hands on the body of Chriſt. Now when that
bloody Wolf had devoured the conſecrated ſop, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks all thoſe
indigeſted Gobbets unworthy receivers take in, were now contained in his
belly; God therefore provides that belly ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ript up, and
thoſe bowels guſh out, that theſe horrible profanations, even in their
Dams belly, might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Deaths wound. The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, ſaith
<hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> was puniſh'd worſe than the woman, the woman
worſe than the man; <hi>Iſabel</hi> that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd the miſchief, worſe
than <hi>Ahab</hi> that took away the vineyard: ſo thou that art the moving
cauſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers deſtruction, muſt look for an heavier torment than
thoſe thou haſt ſeduced: the people of God were plagued for ſinning
with the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Midian,</hi> but the <hi>Midianite</hi> was worſe
plagued for laying thoſe <hi>ſtumbling-blocks</hi> before the people of
God.</p>
            <p>What a ſpotted Chronicle attends that Son of <hi>Nebat,
Jeroboam,</hi> he that ſet up his glittering Calves to keep the people from
the Temple of God! this ſcandalous affront was ſo taken to 
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:99495:75"/> heart, that almoſt in every page it is complain'd of:
whenſoever the ſlips of other Princes fall into mention, <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>
is cry'd out of as the ring-leader; <hi>Jeroboam the Son of</hi> Nebat <hi>that
made</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſin.</hi> So hateful to God was the offenſive
Idolatry of this man, that even long before he rejected the Tribe
<hi>Jeroboam</hi> came of, <hi>he choſe not the Tribe of</hi> Ephraim (as the
Pſalm ſpeaks)<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.67.</note> and
<hi>Theodoret</hi> venters to tell you why, Becauſe it was of this Tribe
<hi>Jeroboam</hi> deſcended, who pluck'd away Ten Tribes from the Worſhip
of God. Even in this life the plagues of God meet with ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſins, a
blemiſh'd name, outward miſhaps, and the fierce ſting of an accuſing
Conſcience. But our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours woe implies more, <hi>the laſting tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
of another world;</hi> and therefore he ſays, <hi>'twere better a milſtone
was hanged about thy neck, and thou caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea,</hi> than theſe
offences were given; for that Maſſy piece could only ſink thy body to the
Seas bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, but leud and offenſive courſes will at laſt drown both Body
and Soul too in the Sulphurous lake of Hell-fire.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:99495:76"/>Now to keep off the blurs of <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
offences,</hi> or the woes of <hi>offences already come,</hi> I adviſe men to
three things; <hi>Reſtitution, Circumſpection, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, in caſe of offences already given, I adviſe
<hi>Reſtitution.</hi> For can we think Almighty God takes more care of our
Silver, than of our Souls? no! one Soul is of more value with him, than the
wealth of the whole world: if then he will have <hi>Zacheus</hi> reſtore that
baſe Metal that was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly taken away, how much more doth he look ſome
amends ſhould be made for a pretious, for an immortal Soul? have thy publick
aberrations given the world an offence? let thy publick amendment proclaim thee
to be a new man. As thoſe Eaſtern <hi>Sages</hi> while they ſtay'd with
<hi>Herod,</hi> loſt the ſight of the Star, but when they left
<hi>Herod</hi> met with it again: ſo if thou haſt loſt the ſplendor of
thy good name, by wallowing in a known ſin, recover it again by forſaking
thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious courſes. Haſt thou drawn men by thy leud ſuggeſtions? draw
them to God by thy good Counſels; if that fail, by thy fervent prayer: if 
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:99495:76"/> the ſame parties thou canſt not reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, bring in
others inſtead of them; as, if thou haſt borrowed ſo many Crowns and
couldſt not repay the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pieces, it is enough if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn an
equivalent ſum. But thou wilt ſay, It lies not in my power to do this, I
ſhall but get mocks, and do no good. Let not that obſtruct thy holy
endeavours; for whether they turn or no, thou ſhalt be no looſer; the God
of Heaven is a gratious pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter; and as the hired labourer that hath
digged in the garden, or held the plow, hath not his payment deferred till the
flowers blowe, or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt appear, but is immediately diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, though
thoſe proſper not: ſo if thou work in the vineyard of God by thy good
Counſels, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examples, whether the fruit be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to thy
pains, or not, thou ſhalt be ſure of <hi>thy reward in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Since theſe things are thus, ſince every
ſtumbling-block we lay in our brothers way, doth but kindle our flame higher
in the next world; <hi>what manner of perſons ought we to be!</hi> how holy
and ſpotleſs in our converſe! how ſtrict and cautelous in our lives, 
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:99495:77"/> like thoſe nimble Creatures in <hi>Ezekiel?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 1.</note> what a ſort of Eyes had we need have on all
ſides? how importunately ſhould we invoke God, <hi>to order our ſteps
aright, that we hurt not our feet againſt the ſtones!</hi> to keep the dore
of our mouth, that we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend not with our tongues; and the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of our
eyes, that they gaze not on forbidden objects; to manacle our hands from
violence and oppreſſion, and reſtrain our feet from revenge! how
diligently ſhould we all watch, leſt we enter our ſelves and draw others
with us into temptation?</p>
            <p n="3">3. But if offences will come in ſpight of our
circumſpection, our Saviours Counſel may help all; do but cut off theſe
offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing parts with the keen razor of a <hi>ſober mortification,</hi> and
thou art ſafe; whether it be a wanton eye, or a griping fiſt, or a foot too
ſwift in the purſuit of a bloody revenge; whether it be a licentious
tongue, or a quaffing Weazand, or the lap of a ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous weed; whatſoever
irregular luſt it be that <hi>laieth a ſtumbling block, an occaſion to
fall in thy brothers way,</hi> do but pare them away with the dreadful
remembrance of their imminent woe, leſt the offending part being now
ſpar'd, thy whole body be afterward caſt into Hell.</p>
            <trailer>Now to God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed
all honour and glory, world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99495:77"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99495:78"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:99495:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99495:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99495:79"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99495:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99495:80"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99495:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99495:81"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99495:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99495:82"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:99495:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:99495:83"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:99495:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:99495:84"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:99495:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:99495:85"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:99495:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99495:86"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99495:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99495:87"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99495:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:99495:88"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:99495:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99495:89"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:99495:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:99495:90"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:99495:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:99495:91"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
